
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
<atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://www.anandtech.com/rss/" />
<title>AnandTech</title>
<description>This channel features the latest computer hardware related articles.</description>
<link>http://www.anandtech.com</link>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2023 AnandTech</copyright>
<dc:creator>Anand Lal Shimpi</dc:creator>
<image>
    <url>http://www.anandtech.com/content/images/rss_logo.png</url>
    <title>AnandTech</title>
    <link>http://www.anandtech.com</link>
</image>

    
<item>
    <title>The AMD Ryzen 9 7950X3D Review: AMD&#39;s Fastest Gaming Processor</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>This week is the long-awaited launch of AMD&#39;s second generation of V-Cache equipped consumer chips, the Ryzen 7000X3D family. Aimed primarily at gamers, tomorrow morning AMD will be releasing a pair of their latest-generation Ryzen 7000 chips with the extra cache stacked on, including the Ryzen 9 7950X3D (16C/32T)&nbsp;and the Ryzen 7 7900X3D (12C/24T). Both chips build upon their Ryzen 7000X-series predecessors by adding a further 64MB of L3 cache, bringing them to an impressive total of 128 MB of L3&nbsp;cache.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, a third SKU, the AMD Ryzen 7 7800X3D, is in the works for April 6th. That part will offer 8 CPU cores and 96 MB of L3 cache, making it the most direct successor to the Ryzen 7 5800X3D.</p>

<p>Ultimately, all three chips will serve to update AMD&#39;s product stack by combining the strengths of the Zen 4 CPU architecture with the performance benefits of the extra L3 cache, which during the overlapping period of the last several months, has been split between the Ryzen 5000 and Ryzen 7000 families. In short, PC gamers will finally be able to have their cake and eat it too, gaining access to AMD&#39;s Zen 4 microarchitecture and its myriad of benefits (higher IPC, higher clockspeeds, DDR5, PCIe 5) with a nice helping of additional L3 cache slathered on top.</p>

<p>From that stack, today we&#39;re reviewing the new flagship Ryzen 9 7950X3D. The 7950X3D offers 16 Zen 4 cores spread over two CCDs (8C/16T per CCD). AMD had to elect one of the CCDs to stack the additional L3 cache onto, resulting in a new-to-AMD heterogeneous CPU design, but&nbsp;they do have some special&nbsp;sauce as a garnish to make it work. We aim to determine if the Ryzen 9 7950X3D is the chip gamers have been yearning for and how it stacks up against other Ryzen 7000 chips (and Intel&#39;s 13th Gen) in our test suite.</p>
<p align="center"><a href='http://dynamic1.anandtech.com/www/delivery/ck.php?n=a1f2f01f&amp;cb=135505679' target='_blank'><img src='http://dynamic1.anandtech.com/www/delivery/avw.php?zoneid=24&amp;cb=135505679&amp;n=a1f2f01f' border='0' alt='' /></a><img src="http://toptenreviews.122.2o7.net/b/ss/tmn-test/1/H.27.3--NS/0" height="1" width="1" border="0" alt="" /></p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18747/the-amd-ryzen-9-7950x3d-review-amd-s-fastest-gaming-processor</link>
 	<pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 09:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18747:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>The Cooler Master V SFX Platinum 1100 PSU Review: Testing the Limits of SFX</title>
    <dc:creator>E. Fylladitakis</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Today we&#39;re looking at a rather remarkable power supply from prolific peripherals producer Cooler Master. The company has put together a 1100 Watt, ATX 3.0 compliant unit that fits entirely within the SFX form factor for compact PCs. The resulting PSU is by far the most power-dense unit we&#39;ve ever reviewed, and is a significant feat of engineering in and of itself.</p>

<p>But Cooler Master and their OEM, Sysgration, are also testing the practical limits of the SFX form factor with their design. Even with no cubic inch wasted, regulating over a kilowatt of energy &ndash; and spiking as high as two kilowatts &ndash; is a lot of work for such a small power supply. So Cooler Master has needed to make some trade-offs here in terms of price and power quality in order to meet their overall power delivery requirements, resulting in a PSU that does well at delivering raw power, but it&#39;s especially well-rounded overall.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18746/the-cooler-master-v-sfx-platinum-1100-psu-review</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 10:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18746:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Cases/Cooling/PSUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>The Montech Titan Gold 1200W PSU Review: A Capable Contender for the ATX 3.0 Club</title>
    <dc:creator>E. Fylladitakis</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Today we are taking a look at a new high-end power supply from industry newcomer Montech. Coming off the success of their mid-power units like the Century Gold series, the company is taking the next step to establishing a full top-to-bottom PSU product stack with the release of their first family of ATX 3.0 units, the Titan Gold Family.</p>

<p>Based on a proven Channel-Well Technologies design that has been upgraded to add the 12VHPWR connector and meet ATX 3.0 compliance, Montech is in a position to make a strong start. Especially as the company isn&#39;t afraid to competitively price their Titan Gold PSUs, even as ATX 3.0 units are only available from a handful of vendors. With 1200 Watts of power on hand, the Titan Gold 1200W is equipped to drive all but the most power-hungry of systems.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18736/the-montech-titan-gold-1200w-atx-30-psu-review-capable-contender</link>
 	<pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 08:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18736:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Cases/Cooling/PSUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Silicon Motion SM2268XT DRAM-less NVMe SSD Controller: PCIe 4.0 Speeds on a Budget</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18745/silicon-motion-sm2268xt-dramless-nvme-ssd-controller-pcie-40-speeds-on-a-budget"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18745/smi-2268xt-carousel_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>The excitement in the client SSD space recently has understandably been on the Gen 5 front. However, cooling requirements have made it difficult for vendors to bring effective M.2 NVMe Gen 5 SSDs to the market. In that context, it appears that Gen 4 M.2 SSDs will continue to have a much longer runway than was previously estimated. In order to better serve that market segment, Silicon Motion is introducing a new product in their PCIe 4.0-capable NVMe SSD controller lineup. The company&#39;s roadmap is not much of a secret, as we do expect their Gen 5 client controllers to land in Q4 2023 - in fact, an end product based on it from ADATA was already demonstrated by ADATA at the 2023 CES. However, today marks the official launch date for the SM2268XT - the third-generation DRAM-less Gen 4 SSD controller meant to play in the entry-level segment in terms of pricing, but move to the high end in terms of performance .</p>

<p>The key updates in the SM2268XT over the SM2267XT and SM2269XT are the increase in the per-channel data rate from 1600 MT/s to 3200 MT/s and support for the latest 2xx layer 3D TLC (as well as QLC) from different flash vendors. The new controller also brings in support for some NVMe 2.0 features (compared to NVMe 1.4 in the SM2267XT and SM2269XT). Like the SM2269XT, the LDPC engine codeword size in the SM2268XT is also 4KB (compared to 2KB in the SM2267XT). The move to a 12nm process also brings in better power efficiency.</p>

<p>THE SM2268XT will be competing against in-house controllers from Western Digital (such as the one used in the WD_BLACK SN770), and the upcoming Phison E21T as well as InnoGrit&#39;s RainierQX IG5220. The claimed performance numbers across all four corners for the SM2268XT are leading in its class.</p>

<table align="center" border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td colspan="6" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle; ">Silicon Motion Client/Consumer Gen 4 NVMe SSD Controllers</td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td style="width: 15%">&nbsp;</td>
			<td style="width: 17%">SM2264</td>
			<td style="width: 17%">SM2267</td>
			<td style="width: 17%">SM2267XT</td>
			<td style="width: 17%">SM2269XT</td>
			<td style="width: 17%">SM2268XT</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle; ">Market Segment</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">High-End Consumer</td>
			<td colspan="4" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">Mainstream Consumer</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Manufacturing<br />
			Process</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">12nm</td>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">28nm</td>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">12nm</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Arm CPU Cores</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;">4x ARM Cortex R8</td>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center;">2x ARM Cortex R5</td>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center;">2x ARM Cortex R8</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Error Correction</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;">4KB LDPC</td>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center;">2KB LDPC</td>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center;">4KB LDPC</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; ">DRAM Support</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">DDR4, LPDDR4(X)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">DDR3, DDR3L, LPDDR3, DDR4, LPDDR4</td>
			<td colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">None / HMB</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Host Interface</td>
			<td colspan="5" rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;">PCIe 4.0 x4</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" rowspan="1">NAND Channels, Interface Speed</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">8ch<br />
			1600 MT/s</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">8ch<br />
			1200 MT/s</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">4ch<br />
			1200 MT/s</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">4ch<br />
			1600 MT/s</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">4ch<br />
			3200 MT/s</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">CEs per Channel</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;">8</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;">8</td>
			<td colspan="3" style="text-align: center;">4</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Sequential Read</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">7500 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">3900 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">3500 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">5100 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">7400 MB/s</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Sequential Write</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">7000 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">3500 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">3000 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">4800 MB/s</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">6500 MB/s</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">4KB Random Read IOPS</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">1.3M</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">500K</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">500K (HMB) / 200K (No HMB)</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">900K</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">1.2M</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">4KB Random Write IOPS</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">1.2M</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">500K</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">500K</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">900K</td>
			<td style="text-align: center;vertical-align: middle; ">1.2M</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>The company indicates that the SM2268XT is currently sampling to its key customers and the launch of SSDs based on it should be imminent. We expect the usual suspects such as ADATA to announce SSDs based on the new controller soon.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18745/silicon-motion-sm2268xt-dramless-nvme-ssd-controller-pcie-40-speeds-on-a-budget</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 09:30:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18745:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ SSDs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Intel Launches Xeon W-3400 and W-2400 Processors For Workstations: Up to 56 Cores and 112 PCIe 5.0 Lanes</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>For all of the singular focus that Intel has placed on its consumer Core desktop CPU parts in the last few years, you could be forgiven for thinking that Intel has forgotten about their Xeon premium processor lineups for workstations. Between the de facto retirement of Intel&rsquo;s desktop-grade Xeon W-1x00-series lineup, and the repeated delays of Intel&rsquo;s current-generation big silicon parts for servers, the Sapphire Rapids-based 4<sup>th</sup> Generation Xeon Scalable series, there hasn&rsquo;t been much noise from Intel in the workstation space in the last few years. But now that Sapphire Rapids for servers has finally launched, the logjam in Intel&rsquo;s product roadmap has at last cleared out, and Intel is finally in a position to resume cascading their latest silicon into new workstation parts.</p>

<p>This morning Intel is announcing their first top-to-bottom refresh of workstation parts, the Xeon W-3400 and Xeon W-2400 series. Aimed at what Intel is broadly classifying as the Expert Workstation and Mainstream Workstation markets respectively, these chip lineups are intended for use in high-performance desktop workstation setups, particularly those that require more CPU cores, more PCIe lanes, more memory bandwidth, or a combination of all three elements. Based on the same Sapphire Rapids silicon as Intel&rsquo;s recently-launched server parts, the new Xeon W SKUs will bring down many (but not all) of the features that have come to define Intel&rsquo;s leading-edge server silicon, along with a new chipset and motherboards that are more suitable for use in high-performance workstations.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18741/intel-launches-xeon-w-3400-and-w-2400-processors-for-workstations-up-to-56-cores-and-112-pcie-5-0-lanes</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 12:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18741:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Western Digital Launches 22 TB HDD for Consumers in Updated My Book Portfolio</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18743/western-digital-launches-22-tb-consumer-hdds-in-updated-my-book-portfolio"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18743/carousel_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Western Digital&#39;s 22 TB hard disk drives <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17501/western-digital-22tb-wd-gold-red-pro-and-purple-hdds-hit-retail">hit retail in July 2022</a>, with a trio of products catering to the prosumer and business / enterprise markets. Today, the company is announcing an update to their portfolio of HDD-using direct-attached storage products - the My Book and My Book Duo. These products now come in new SKUs utilizing 22 TB HDDs tweaked for consumer workloads.</p>

<p>The My Book is an external storage solution that comes with a USB 3.2 Gen 1 Type-A interface and utilizes a single hard disk. It requires an external power adapter. On the other hand, the My Book Duo is a dual-drive solution with hardware RAID. By default, the drives are configured in RAID-0. The product also includes hub functionality. It comes with a USB 3.2 Gen 1 Type-C interface and also has two USB 3.2 Gen 1 Type-A downstream ports. Both products come with 256-bit hardware encryption support (requires WD Security software installation on client system to configure and use passwords). The WD Backup software component is also available for both systems in order to enable easy configuration of backups.</p>

<p>Previous WD My Book Duo releases <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/11756">used WD Red hard drives</a>, but the company has not publicly confirmed the nature of the 22 TB HDD used in the new SKUs. No performance numbers were provided, but it is expected to be in the same ballpark as the previous generation SKUs.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18743/western-digital-launches-22-tb-consumer-hdds-in-updated-my-book-portfolio"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18743/mybook-22t_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1" style="width: 100%;">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td colspan="9" style="vertical-align: middle;">Western Digital&#39;s WD My Book (2023) External Storage Devices</td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;" width="12%">Capacity</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="16%">Transfer Rate</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="12%">Interface</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="25%">Dimensions</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="28%">Model Number</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="10%">Price</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">4 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="8" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">Up to<br />
			250 MB/s,<br />
			depends on model</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="8" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">USB 3.2 Gen 1 Type-A</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="8" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">Height: 170.6 mm / 6.7&rdquo;<br />
			Length: 139.3 mm / 5.5&rdquo;<br />
			Width: 49 mm / 1.9&quot;</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0040HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B01LQQHL4E">$95</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">6 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0060HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B01LQQHKZY">$119</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">8 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0080HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B01LQQHLGC">$140</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">12 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0120HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B07X3RBTQT">$237</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">14 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0140HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B07YD3LPNZ">$280</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">16 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0160HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B08KTSWHZB">$330</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">18 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0180HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B08KTQWV7Z">$300</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">22 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBBGB0220HBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=WDBBGB0220HBK">$600</a></td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18743/western-digital-launches-22-tb-consumer-hdds-in-updated-my-book-portfolio"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18743/mybookduo-44t_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1" style="width: 100%;">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td colspan="9" style="vertical-align: middle;">Western Digital&#39;s WD My Book Duo (2023) External Storage Devices</td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;" width="12%">Capacity</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="16%">Transfer Rate</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="12%">Interface</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="25%">Dimensions</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="28%">Model Number</td>
			<td style="vertical-align: middle;" width="10%">Price</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">16 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="6" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">Up to<br />
			360 MB/s?,<br />
			depends on model</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="6" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">USB 3.2 Gen 1 Type-C</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="6" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">Height: 180 mm / 7.09&rdquo;<br />
			Length: 160 mm / 6.3&rdquo;<br />
			Width: 100 mm / 3.94&quot;</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBFBE0160JBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B074QW86T4">$440</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">20 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBFBE0200JBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B074R34DD3">$668</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">24 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBFBE0240JBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://amzn.com/s/?tag=anandtech01-20&amp;field-keywords=B07Y2PRTWY">$900</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">28 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBFBE0280JBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1512867-REG/wd_wdbfbe0280jbk_nesn_28tb_my_book_duo.html">$1200</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">36 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBFBE0360JBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://www.westerndigital.com/products/external-drives/wd-my-book-duo-usb-3-1-hdd#WDBFBE0360JBK-NESN">$1500</a></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">44 TB</td>
			<td colspan="1" style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><small>WDBFBE0440JBK</small></td>
			<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;"><a href="https://www.westerndigital.com/products/external-drives/wd-my-book-duo-usb-3-1-hdd#WDBFBE0440JBK-NESN">$1500</a></td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>The company already has the new SKUs available for purchase in the retail market. The 22 TB My Book is priced at $600 (commensurate with the pricing of the bare 22 TB drives introduced last year), while the 44 TB My Book Duo is priced at $1500. A $300 premium for a RAID-0 / RAID-1 controller and a couple of downstream USB 3.2 Gen 1 Type-A ports appears very steep, but that is the premium the company expects early adopters to pay (and is par for the course, based on how the previous My Book Duo SKUs were priced at launch). The single HDD My Book looks to be a cost-effective solution for consumers looking for an off-the-shelf backup solution with high capacity requirements.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18743/western-digital-launches-22-tb-consumer-hdds-in-updated-my-book-portfolio</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 08:30:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18743:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Western Digital]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>ASRock Industrial&#39;s 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 Series Brings Zen 3+ and USB4 40Gbps to UCFF Systems</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18742/asrock-industrials-4x4-box-7000d5-series-brings-zen-3-and-usb4-40gbps-to-ucff-systems"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18742/4x4box-7k-carousel_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>ASRock Industrial&#39;s lineup of ultra-compact form-factor machines in the NUC BOX (Intel-based) and 4X4 BOX (AMD-based) series has gained popularity over the last couple of years. Being the first to market with the latest platforms has been one of the key reasons behind this. In 2022, the company had launched the Intel Alder Lake and AMD Cezanne UCFF systems together, with the NUC BOX-1200 series and the 4X4 BOX-5000 series becoming available for purchase within a few weeks of each other. Earlier this year, the Intel Raptor Lake-based NUC BOX-1300 series was launched (our <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18732/asrock-industrial-nucs-box1360pd4-review-raptor-lakep-ecc">review</a>) and is already available for purchase. The company recently took the wraps off the 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 series based on AMD&#39;s low-power Rembrandt-R APUs. These APUs sport Zen 3+ cores along with a RDNA2 iGPU fabricated on a TSMC 6nm process.</p>

<p>One of the key updates in the new 4X4 BOX systems is the move to DDR5 SODIMMs. The other updates in the platform such as support for a PCIe 4.0 x4 M.2 NVMe SSD and USB4 40 Gbps bring it almost on par with the premium UCFF systems based on Intel processors. Full-fledged USB4 support inclusive of PCIe tunneling has been somewhat of a hit or miss on AMD platforms, as many OEMs have refrained from integrating the necessary board components to enable it. AMD itself had some work to do on the firmware side before the feature baked into the hardware of Rembrandt and later APUs could be enabled. The good news here is that the ASRock Industrial 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 series has two USB4 ports capable of supporting DisplayPort 1.4 signals as well as PCIe tunneling - this means that Thunderbolt 3 peripherals should work when connected to those Type-C ports.</p>

<p>The 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 series comes in two flavors. The specifications of both models are summarized in the table below.</p>

<table style="width: 100%;">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td align="center" colspan="4" style="vertical-align: middle;">ASRock Industrial 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 (Rembrandt-R) Lineup</td>
		</tr>
		<tr align="center" class="tlblue">
			<td colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Model</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 40%;">4X4 BOX-7735U/D5</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 40%;">4X4 BOX-7535U/D5</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">CPU</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">AMD Ryzen 7 7735U<br />
			8C / 16T<br />
			2.7 GHz (Up to 4.75 GHz)<br />
			28W</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">AMD Ryzen 5 7535U<br />
			6C / 12T<br />
			2.9 GHz (Up to 4.55 GHz)<br />
			28W</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">GPU</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">AMD Radeon 680M<br />
			(12 CU / 768 Shaders) @ 2.2 GHz</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">AMD Radeon 660M<br />
			(6 CU / 384 Shaders) @ 1.9 GHz</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">DRAM</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Two DDR5 SO-DIMM slots<br />
			Up to 64 GB of DDR5-4800 in dual-channel mode</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Motherboard</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.02&quot; x 4.09&quot; UCFF</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Storage</td>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle;">SSD</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1x M.2-22(42/60/80) (PCIe 4.0 x4 (CPU-direct))</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle;">DFF</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 &times; SATA III Port (for 2.5&quot; drive)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Wireless</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mediatek MT7922 (RZ616)? Wi-Fi 6E<br />
			2x2 802.11ax Wi-Fi (2.4Gbps) + Bluetooth 5.2 module</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Ethernet</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1x 2.5 GbE RJ-45 (Realtek RTL8125)<br />
			1x GbE RJ-45 (Realtek RTL8111EPV with DASH Support)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">USB</td>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle;">Front</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 &times; USB 3.2 Gen 2 Type-A<br />
			2x USB4 (with DisplayPort 1.4a Alt Mode)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle;">Rear</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">2 &times; USB 2.0 Type-A</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Display Outputs</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 &times; HDMI 2.1 (Rear, up to 8Kp60)<br />
			1 &times; DisplayPort 1.4a (Rear, up to 4Kp60)<br />
			2 &times; DisplayPort 1.4a (using Front Panel Type-C ports, up to 4Kp60)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Audio</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">1 &times; 3.5mm audio jack (Realtek ALC233)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">PSU</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">External (19V/90W)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Dimensions</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Length: 117.5 mm<br />
			Width: 110 mm<br />
			Height: 47.85 mm</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>Note that the M.2 2280 support is enabled by a separate bracket, similar to the previous NUC BOX and 4X4 BOX systems with 2.5&quot; drive support and dual LAN capabilities.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18742/asrock-industrials-4x4-box-7000d5-series-brings-zen-3-and-usb4-40gbps-to-ucff-systems"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18742/4x4box-mid-page_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>Overall, these systems bring the AMD UCFF scene on par with the high-end Intel NUCs and its clones - except for the newer NUC BOX-1300/D5 series which has Thunderbolt 4 ports that also have USB 3.2 Gen 2x2 support for 20Gbps PSSDs. The USB4 ports in the 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 support only up to USB 3.2 Gen 2 speeds in legacy USB (non-PCIe tunneling) mode. The RDNA2 iGPU in the new machines should also help these systems perform as well as the the Alder Lake and Raptor Lake mini-PCs in graphics-heavy workloads.</p>

<p>We have reached out to ASRock Industrial for clarity on market availability dates and pricing, and will update the article with the details after receiving them (<strong>Update - Feb 15, 2023</strong>: The systems will be available for purchase in mid-March 2023. The 4X4 BOX-7735U/D5 will have a pre-tax MSRP of $650, and the 4X4 BOX-7535U/D5 will have a pre-tax MSRP of $500).</p>

<p><div>Gallery: <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8229" target="_blank">ASRock Industrial's 4X4 BOX 7000/D5 Series Brings Zen 3+ and USB4 40Gbps to UCFF Systems</a><div><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8229#1" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8229/4x4box-7k-carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8229#2" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8229/4x4box-mid-page_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a></div></div></p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18742/asrock-industrials-4x4-box-7000d5-series-brings-zen-3-and-usb4-40gbps-to-ucff-systems</link>
 	<pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 13:05:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18742:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Systems]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>The MSI MPG A1000G PCIE5 PSU Review: Balance of Power</title>
    <dc:creator>E. Fylladitakis</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Back in December, we had the opportunity to take a look at MSI&#39;s MEG A1300P power supply, the company&#39;s latest flagship PSU. Besides offering plenty of power, the MEG Ai1300P was also MSI&#39;s first ATX 3.0 power supplies &ndash; and one of the first ATX 3.0 PSUs on the market overall. And while it was admittedly not a groundbreaking design overall, it was still a seminal work of sorts, sketching out a rough picture of what we should expect from other ATX 3.0 PSU designs, including MSI&#39;s own.</p>

<p>The MEG Ai1300P was a true flagship PSU, for all the pros and cons that come with that. As impressive as it was overall, it was also aimed at those willing and able to deal with the hefty price tag. This is all well and good for the small fraction of the market that can afford such a high caliber PSU, but for most PC builders, budgets are a very real thing.</p>

<p>So, for today&rsquo;s review, we are taking a look at something a little more downmarket from MSI: their MPG series. Like their flagship units, the new MPG PSUs are also are ATX 3.0 Ready, but they come at more reasonable prices. Despite that shift, the unit we&#39;re testing today, the MPG A1000G, is still one of the most powerful PSUs MSI offers (as well as being the top MPG unit), capable of delivering a kilowatt of PC power.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18720/msi-mpg-a1000g-pcie5-psu-review-balanced-power</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 13:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18720:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Cases/Cooling/PSUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>AMD’s Ryzen 7000X3D Chips Get Release Dates: February 28th and April 6th, For $699/$599/$449</title>
    <dc:creator>Ryan Smith</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>AMD today has announced the launch date and prices for its eagerly anticipated Ryzen 7000X3D series processors. Aimed primarily at gamers, the company&rsquo;s first L3 V-Cache equipped Ryzen 7000 processors will begin rolling out on February 28<sup>th</sup>, when the Ryzen 9 7950X3D and Ryzen 9 7900X3D go on sale for $699 and $599 respectively. This will be followed up by the Ryzen 7 7800X3D a bit over a month later, when it goes on sale for $449 on April 6<sup>th</sup>.</p>

<p>First announced to great fanfare during <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18709/amd-unveils-ryzen-9-7950x3d-7900x3d-and-ryzen-7-7800x3d-up-to-128-mb-of-l3-cache-and-5-7-ghz-boost">AMD&rsquo;s CES 2023 keynote</a> (and teased well before that), the Ryzen 7000X3D chips will be AMD&rsquo;s second generation of consumer chips employing the company&rsquo;s novel 3D stacked V-Cache technology. V-Cache allows AMD to stack a 64MB L3 cache die on top of their existing CCDs in order to expand the total L3 capacity of a Zen 3/4 CCD, going from 32MB to 96MB. And in the case of multi-CCD designs such as the Ryzen 9 7950X, bringing the total, chip-wide L3 cache pool to 128MB.</p>

<table border="0" style="text-align:center" width="95%">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td colspan="8">AMD Ryzen 7000X/X3D Series Line-Up</td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td><i>AnandTech</i></td>
			<td>Cores<br />
			Threads</td>
			<td>Base<br />
			Freq</td>
			<td>Turbo<br />
			Freq</td>
			<td>L3<br />
			Cache</td>
			<td>TDP</td>
			<td>Price<br />
			(Street)</td>
			<td>Release<br />
			Date</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey"><strong>Ryzen 9 7950X3D</strong></td>
			<td><strong>16C / 32T</strong></td>
			<td><strong>4.2 GHz</strong></td>
			<td><strong>5.7 GHz</strong></td>
			<td><strong>128&nbsp;MB</strong></td>
			<td><strong>120W</strong></td>
			<td><strong>$699</strong></td>
			<td><strong>02/28/23</strong></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Ryzen 9 7950X</td>
			<td>16C / 32T</td>
			<td>4.5 GHz</td>
			<td>5.7 GHz</td>
			<td>64 MB</td>
			<td>170W</td>
			<td><a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-7950X-32-Thread-Unlocked-Processor%2Fdp%2FB0BBHD5D8Y%3Fth%3D1%26tag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-1327878356486651400-20">$583</a></td>
			<td>-</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="8">&nbsp;</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey"><strong>Ryzen 9 7900X3D</strong></td>
			<td><strong>12C / 24T</strong></td>
			<td><strong>4.4 GHz</strong></td>
			<td><strong>5.6 GHz</strong></td>
			<td><strong>128 MB</strong></td>
			<td><strong>120W</strong></td>
			<td><strong>$599</strong></td>
			<td><strong>02/28/23</strong></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Ryzen 9 7900X</td>
			<td>12C / 24T</td>
			<td>4.7 GHz</td>
			<td>5.6 GHz</td>
			<td>64 MB</td>
			<td>170W</td>
			<td><a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-7900X-24-Thread-Unlocked-Processor%2Fdp%2FB0BBJ59WJ4%3Fth%3D1%26tag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-6231689756408712000-20">$444</a></td>
			<td>-</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="8">&nbsp;</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey"><strong>Ryzen 7 7800X3D</strong></td>
			<td><strong>8C / 16T</strong></td>
			<td><strong>4.2 GHz</strong></td>
			<td><strong>5.0 GHz</strong></td>
			<td><strong>96 MB</strong></td>
			<td><strong>120W</strong></td>
			<td><strong>$449</strong></td>
			<td><strong>04/06/23</strong></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Ryzen 7 7700X</td>
			<td>8C / 16T</td>
			<td>4.5 GHz</td>
			<td>5.4 GHz</td>
			<td>32 MB</td>
			<td>105W</td>
			<td><a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-7700X-16-Thread-Unlocked-Processor%2Fdp%2FB0BBHHT8LY%3Ftag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-3725827067875564000-20">$299</a></td>
			<td>-</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Ryzen 7 5800X3D</td>
			<td>8C / 16T</td>
			<td>3.4 GHz</td>
			<td>4.5 GHz</td>
			<td>96 MB</td>
			<td>105W</td>
			<td><a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-5800X3D-16-Thread-Processor-Technology%2Fdp%2FB09VCJ2SHD%3Ftag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-1541036193893498400-20">$323</a></td>
			<td>-</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>Following the successful trial of the technology in the consumer space with AMD&rsquo;s original Ryzen 7 5800X3D, which was released to positive acclaim back in the spring of 2022, AMD has developed a much broader lineup of V-Cache equipped Ryzen chips for this generation. This includes not only the 5800X3D&rsquo;s direct successor, the 8 core Ryzen 7 7800X3D, but also, for the first time, chips employing multiple CCDs. These are the Ryzen 9 7900X3D and 7950X3D, which will offer 12 and 16 CPU cores, respectively.</p>

<p>Interestingly, AMD has gone for a non-homogenous design for these multi-CCD parts &ndash; rather than giving both CCDs V-Cache, AMD is only outfitting one of the CCDs with the extra L3 cache. The other CCD will remain a plain Zen 4 CCD, with its integrated 32MB of L3 cache. The unbalanced design, besides allowing AMD to control the costs of what&rsquo;s still a relatively expensive technology to implement, will allow AMD to offer something close to the best of both worlds for their multi-CCD parts. The V-Cache equipped Zen 4 CCDs will offer 6 or 8 CPU cores backed by the massive L3 pool, for tasks that benefit from the larger cache size, while the vanilla Zen 4 CCDs will be unencumbered by the V-Cache, allowing them to clock higher for pure throughput workloads that wouldn&rsquo;t benefit from the extra cache.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18737/amds-ryzen-7000x3d-chips-releasing-february-28th-and-april-6th"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18737/AMD%20CES%202023%20-%20Client%20Processors%20Press%20Deck_40_575px.png" /></a></p>

<p>As with the original 5800X3D, AMD is aiming these chips at gamers in particular, as the complex, heavy-dataset nature of video games means they often benefit from having additional L3 cache on-hand. The 5800X3D was, depending on the game, around 15% faster than its vanilla Ryzen counterpart &ndash; at least so long as it wasn&rsquo;t GPU limited. AMD is being a bit more coy this time around on making apples-to-apples comparisons against their regular Ryzen 7000 chips, so for now the only official performance figures available from AMD are pitting the chips against the 5800X3D. In lieu of that, a 15% improvement is a reasonable baseline given that the cache sizes haven&rsquo;t changed in the last generation, but we&rsquo;ll definitely want to take a closer look at the final chips to see if the additional L3 cache is as beneficial to Zen 4 as it was for Zen 3.</p>

<p>Back at their CES 2023 keynote, AMD announced the specifications for two-and-a-half of the chips, as well as an undetailed February launch date. With today&rsquo;s announcement, AMD is finally filling in the rest of the details, as well as confirming that only part of the product stack is going to make that February launch date.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18737/amds-ryzen-7000x3d-chips-releasing-february-28th-and-april-6th"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18737/7950X3D%20Die_575px.jpg" /></a><br />
<em>(Image Courtesy <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/amd-unveils-three-ryzen-7000x3d-v-cache-chips-three-new-65w-non-x-cpus-too">Tom&#39;s Hardware</a></em>)</p>

<p>As previously noted, the Ryzen 9 7950X3D and Ryzen 9 7900X3D both launch on February 28<sup>th</sup>. The 16 core 7950X3D will hit the streets with a $699 price tag, while the 12 core 7900X3D will intro at $599. At current street prices, this represents roughly a $100 to $150 premium over the chips&rsquo; regular counterparts, with the 7950X selling for around <a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-7950X-32-Thread-Unlocked-Processor%2Fdp%2FB0BBHD5D8Y%3Fth%3D1%26tag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-1327878356486651400-20">$583</a>, and the 7900X selling for around <a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-7900X-24-Thread-Unlocked-Processor%2Fdp%2FB0BBJ59WJ4%3Fth%3D1%26tag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-6231689756408712000-20">$444</a>. Prices on AMD&rsquo;s top AM5 chips have come down a decent bit since their 2022 launch, so the new X3D SKUs are coming in at similar launch prices as their non V-Cache counterparts. Put another way, whereas $699 would get you a 16 core 7950X in September, come February it will get you the same chip with an additional 64MB of L3 cache.</p>

<p>Other than benchmarks, at this point the only detail we don&rsquo;t have on the 7950X3D and 7900X3D are the clockspeeds for the V-Cache equipped CCDs. AMD&rsquo;s quoted turbo clockspeeds are for the vanilla CCD, so it&rsquo;s unclear just how much clockspeeds have been lowered for the V-Cache CCD. But taking a hint from AMD&rsquo;s sole single CCD X3D part, the 7800X3D, we see that part has a top clockspeed of just 5.0GHz. So we&rsquo;d expect something similar for the V-Cache CCDs on the Ryzen 9 parts.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18737/amds-ryzen-7000x3d-chips-releasing-february-28th-and-april-6th"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18737/AMD_Price_Slide_575px.png" /></a></p>

<p>Speaking of the Ryzen 7 7800X3D, we finally have the full specifications on AMD&rsquo;s most straightforward X3D part. Back in January AMD hadn&rsquo;t locked down the base clockspeeds on this part, but as of today we finally have the answer: 4.2GHz. The chip will, in turn, be able to turbo as high as 5.0GHz as previously noted.</p>

<p>The cheapest of the Z3D parts, with a price tag of $449, the 7800X3D will also be the laggard of the group, with the chip not launching until April 6<sup>th</sup>. AMD has not explained the gap in launch dates, but it&rsquo;s reasonable to assume that AMD is prioritizing the assembly and shipping of their more expensive Ryzen 9 SKUs. In any case, at current street prices the 7800X3D will carry a $150 premium over the <a href="https://target.georiot.com/Proxy.ashx?tsid=45726&amp;GR_URL=https%3A%2F%2Famazon.com%2FAMD-7700X-16-Thread-Unlocked-Processor%2Fdp%2FB0BBHHT8LY%3Ftag%3Dhawk-future-20%26ascsubtag%3Danandtech-us-3725827067875564000-20">$299</a> 7700X, making it a full 50% more expensive, assuming these street prices hold through April. This happens to be the same price the 5800X3D launched at, so AMD is technically just holding the line here, but it does underscore how price cuts on the rest of the Ryzen 7000 lineup have made the standard chips very competitive on a price/performance basis.</p>

<p>In any case, we&rsquo;ll have more on AMD&rsquo;s first V-Cache equipped Zen 4 chips later this month. Besides taking an in-depth look at the performance improvements brought about by the larger L3 cache, the other major factor driving performance is going to be the Windows thread scheduler. As this is AMD&rsquo;s first asymmetric Ryzen CPU, it will be up to Windows and AMD&rsquo;s chipset driver to figure out which CCD to place threads on for the 7950X3D/7900X3D. So this month&rsquo;s launch is going to require that AMD&rsquo;s hardware and software offerings are in sync in order for the company to make a good first impression.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18737/amds-ryzen-7000x3d-chips-releasing-february-28th-and-april-6th</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 21:45:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18737:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Western Digital Unveils Dual Actuator Ultrastar DC HS760 20TB HDD</title>
    <dc:creator>Anton Shilov</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18735/western-digital-unveils-dual-actuator-ultrastar-dc-hs760-20tb-hdd"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18735/wdc-ultrastar-dc-hs760-hdd_575px.png" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Without much fanfare, Western Digital this week introduced its first dual actuator hard drive, a 20TB drive that is designed to offer SATA SSD-like sequential read/write performance. The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.westerndigital.com/en-us/products/internal-drives/data-center-drives/ultrastar-dc-hs760-hdd?cjevent=0e5668f4a14111ed808ec3dd0a18b8f9&amp;utm_medium=afl1&amp;utm_source=cj&amp;utm_content=Data+Recovery+-+US&amp;cp1=8900246&amp;utm_campaign=datarecovery-us&amp;utm_term=04-11-2022&amp;cp2=Future+Publishing+Limited#ultrastar-dc-hs760-20-tb">Ultrastar DC HS760 drive</a>&nbsp;is meant to increase IOPS-per-terabyte performance for hyperscale cloud datacenters and will compete against Seagate&#39;s dual actuator Exos 2X family of HDDs. Meanwhile, Western Digital&#39;s offering will also mark the latest deployment of the company&#39;s OptiNAND technology.</p>

<p>The dual actuator Ultrastar DC HS760 HDD builds upon the company&#39;s single actuator Ultrastar DC HC560 drive which uses nine 2.2TB ePMR (energy-assisted perpendicular magnetic recording) platters. But in the case of the HS760, WD adds a second actuator to the drive, essentially splitting it up into two quasi-independent drives with each half having domain over 4.5 platters (9 surfaces). By doubling the number of indepent actuators, Western Digital claims that the HS760 is able to double sequential read/write speeds and increase random read/write performance by 1.7 times versus single actuator drives.</p>

<p>While the company yet has to upload a datasheet for its dual actuator HDD, we are looking at sequential throughput rates of around 582 MB/s, which interestingly enough is a tad faster than SATA SSDs, which max out the SATA-III at around 550 MB/s. Though it&#39;s worth noting that, as is typical for enterprise-focused hard drives, Western Digital is using Serial Attached SCSI (SAS) here, so it won&#39;t be possible to hook the drive up to a SATA host.</p>

<p>Since the two actuators inside Western Digital&#39;s Ultrastar DC HS760 HDD work independently, the unit presents itself as two independent logical unit number (LUN) devices, and both logical hard drives are independently addressable. This means that datacenters will have to introduce certain software tweaks (i.e., these are not drop-in compatible with infrastructure designed for single actuator HDDs). But for the added complexity on the software/configuration side of matters, data center operators are being promised not only the aforementioned higher performance levels, but also a setup that is 37% more energy efficient in terms of IOPS-per-Watt than two 10TB devices.&nbsp; In essence, hyperscalers are getting many of the benefits of having two current-generation 10TB HDDs, but in a product that takes up the space of just a single drive.</p>

<p>The key advantage of Western Digital&#39;s Ultrastar DC HS760 20TB over hard drives with one actuator of the same capacity is significantly increased&nbsp;performance on an IOPS-per-TB basis. Typical enterprise-grade 3.5-inch HDDs with capacities between 8TB and 16TB offer random performance of 6 &ndash; 10 IOPS per terabyte, which is enough to ensure quality-of-service of datacenters. But at 20TB, random performance drops to less than 5 IOPS per terabyte, which requires hyperscalers to introduce various mitigations to ensure that these drives meet their QoS requirements.</p>

<p>Such mitigations either include implementing command queuing and latency-bounded I/O (LBIO) in firmware, usage of drives of lower capacity, reducing usable capacity per drive, or even adding sophisticated caching methods. All of these methods either increase upfront costs and/or total-costs-of-ownership. Therefore, hyperscalers need drives that can physically increase their IOPS-per-terabyte performance and dual actuator HDDs are a natural answer. As an added bonus, these hard drives also offer two times higher sequential read/write speeds than single-actuator HDDs.</p>

<p>As noted above, Western Digital is not the only company to offer dual actuator HDDs as Seagate has been doing this for years now. But Western Digital&#39;s Ultrastar DC HS760 has an advantage over rivals that comes in the form of its&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/16920/western-digital-reimagines-hdd-flash-integration-with-optinand">OptiNAND</a>&nbsp;technology, which is an integrated iNAND UFS embedded flash drive (EFD) coupled with firmware tweaks. OptiNAND is meant to increase capacity, reliability, and performance of HDDs and while Western Digital yet has to disclose performance numbers of its Ultrastar DC HS760 drives, it is at least evident that its 20TB drive will offer more capacity than Seagate&#39;s competing Exos 2X18 18TB drive.</p>

<p>Otherwise, given that the HS760 is aimed primarily at hyperscalers, Western Digital is treating the drive as a product for a limited audience. Although the drive is listed on the company&#39;s website, for example, there is no public pricing listed, and buyers will have to make a sales inquiry. So the actual unit pricing on the new drive is going to vary some, depending on things like order volumes and agreements between Western Digital and its clients.</p>

<p>Western Digital&#39;s Ultrastar DC HS760 HDD will be covered with a five-year warranty with each LUN rated for a 500 TB annual workload.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18735/western-digital-unveils-dual-actuator-ultrastar-dc-hs760-20tb-hdd</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 10:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18735:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Storage]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Samsung Portable SSD T7 Shield 4TB Review: IP65 PSSD Gets a Capacity Upgrade</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Samsung has been enjoying market success with their lineup of portable SSDs, starting with the T1 back in 2015. The company has been regularly updating their PSSD lineup with the evolution of different high-speed interfaces as well as NAND flash technology.</p>

<p>In early 2022, the company launched the Portable SSD T7 Shield, a follow-up to the Portable SSD T7 (Touch) introduced in early 2020. Introduced in models with capacities up to 2TB, the ruggedness / IP65 rating of the T7 Shield was advertised as a selling point over the regular Portable SSD T7 and T7 Touch. The company launched a 4TB version in this lineup in mid-January for the EU market. Samsung is officially bringing over the new capacity SKU to the North American market today. Read on for a comprehensive look at the performance and value proposition of the Portable SSD T7 Shield 4TB.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18734/samsung-portable-ssd-t7-shield-4tb-review-ip65-pssd-gets-a-capacity-upgrade</link>
 	<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 10:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18734:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Storage]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>ASRock Industrial NUCS BOX-1360P/D4 Review: Raptor Lake-P Impresses, plus Surprise ECC</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Low-power processors have traditionally been geared towards notebooks and other portable platforms. However, the continued popularity of ultra-compact form-factor desktop systems has resulted in UCFF PCs also serving as lead vehicles for the latest mobile processors. Such is the case with Intel&#39;s Raptor Lake-P - the processor SKUs were announced earlier this month at the 2023 CES, and end-products using the processor were slated to appear in a few weeks. Intel is officially allowing its partners to start selling their products into the channel today, and also allowing third-party evaluation results of products based on Raptor Lake-P to be published.</p>

<p>ASRock Industrial announced their Raptor Lake-P-based NUC clones as soon as Intel made the parts public. With the new platform, the company decided to trifurcate their offerings - a slim version (sans 2.5&quot; drive support) with DDR4 SODIMM slots in the NUCS BOX-13x0P/D4, a regular height version with 2.5&quot; drive support in the NUC BOX-13x0P/D4, and a slightly tweaked version of the latter with DDR5 SODIMM slots in the NUC BOX-13x0P/D5. The NUCS BOX-1360P is the company&#39;s flagship in the first category, and the relative maturity of DDR4-based platforms has allowed them to start pushing the product into the channel early.</p>

<p>ASRock Industrial sampled us with a NUCS BOX-1360P/D4 from their first production run. We expected a run of the mill upgrade with improvements in performance and power efficiency. In the course of the review process, we found that the system allowed control over a new / key Raptor Lake-P feature that Intel hadn&#39;t even bothered to bring out during their CES announcement - in-band ECC. Read on for a comprehensive look at Raptor Lake-P&#39;s feature set for desktop platforms with detailed performance and power efficiency analysis.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18732/asrock-industrial-nucs-box1360pd4-review-raptor-lakep-ecc</link>
 	<pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 09:30:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18732:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Systems]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Seagate Confirms 30TB+ HAMR HDDs in Q3, Envisions 50TB Drives in a Few Years</title>
    <dc:creator>Anton Shilov</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18733/seagate-confirms-30tb-hamr-hdds-in-q3-envisions-50tb-drives-in-a-few-years"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18733/HAMR-actuator-and-disks-illustration-22_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Seagate this week confirmed plans to launch the industry&#39;s first 30+ TB hard drive that uses its heat assisted magnetic recording (HAMR) technology, as well as reaffirming its commitment to release HDDs with capacities of 50 TB and higher in a few years. But before this happens, the company will release 22 TB and 24 TB HDDs that will rely on perpendicular magnetic recording (PMR) and shingled magnetic recording (SMR) technologies, respectively.</p>

<h3>One More Play for PMR and SMR</h3>

<p>Various energy assisted magnetic recording methods, such as HAMR, will be used for next generations of hard drives for years to come. But while PMR is running out of steam, it is still evolving. Seagate has managed to increase areal density enabled by its PMR + TDMR platform by around 10%, enabling 2.2 TB 3.5-inch HDD platters and thus 22 TB hard drives featuring 10 of such disks. Furthermore, by using shingled recording, these drives can have their capacity stretched to 24 TB.</p>

<p>These 22 TB and 24 TB Seagate Exos drives will likely be drop-in compatible with existing cloud datacenter hardware as well as infrastructure, and should not require extensive validation and certification procedures, unlike brand-new HAMR HDDs. As a result, Seagate&#39;s customers will be able to deploy such hard drives fairly quickly and increase storage density and storage capacity of their datacenters.</p>

<p>Seagate is now ramping up production of its 22 TB hard drives for datacenters, so expect the company to start their shipments shortly. Seagate is not disclosing when exactly it will officially launch its 22 TB and 24 TB parts, but we would expect them to arrive before the company introduces its HAMR-based HDDs; so think Q1 or Q2.</p>

<h3>30+ TB HDDs Coming in Q3</h3>

<p>In fact, Seagate has been shipping HAMR HDDs to select customers for evaluation as well as inside its own Lyve storage systems for a while, but those drives featured capacities akin to those of PMR/CMR HDDs and were not available in huge volumes. With Seagate&#39;s 2<sup>nd</sup>&nbsp;generation HAMR platform, the company is going after higher volumes, but it took the company quite some time to get there. The first pre-qualification high-capacity HAMR-based HDDs are only just now getting ready to head out to customers for evaluation.</p>

<p>&quot;We are meeting or exceeding all product development milestones and reliability metrics, and we will be shipping pre-qualification units to key cloud customers in the coming weeks,&quot;&nbsp;<a href="https://s24.q4cdn.com/101481333/files/doc_financials/2023/q2/CORRECTED-TRANSCRIPT_-Seagate-Technology-Holdings-Plc(STX-US),-Q2-2023-Earnings-Call,-25-January-2023-5_00-PM-ET.1.pdf">said</a>&nbsp;Dave Mosley, chief executive of Seagate.&nbsp;</p>

<p><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18733/seagate-confirms-30tb-hamr-hdds-in-q3-envisions-50tb-drives-in-a-few-years"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18733/HAMR-actuator-head-and-laser-illustration_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>Meanwhile, commercial HAMR hard drives with capacities of 30TB or higher will ship in third quarter of this year, which is in-line with what Seagate promised last year.</p>

<p>&quot;As a result of this progress, we now expect to launch our 30-plus terabyte platform in the June quarter, slightly ahead of schedule,&quot; said Mosley. &quot;The speed of the initial HAMR volume ramp will depend on a number of factors, including product yields and&nbsp;customer qualification timelines.&quot;</p>

<p>Initially Seagate will only offer its HAMR technology for its highest-capacity offerings for hyperscale datacenters, whom need maximum storage density and are willing to pay premium for the drives and for supporting infrastructure. As yields of HAMR-supporting media and the appropriate read/write heads increase, the technology will be applied for drives with lower capacities in a bid to cut down their production costs (fewer disks and heads, lower the costs). This is not going to happen overnight though, as the company needs to increase yields of HAMR drive components and the HDDs themselves to a comfortable level.</p>

<p>&quot;I think this year, [the volume of HAMR HDDs] will probably still be relatively low,&quot; said the head of Seagate. &quot;Then the faster we can get the yields and scrap and all the costs that we can control down on the heads and media, then the faster we&#39;ll be accelerating. I think that will happen in calendar year 2024 and calendar year 2025 will just continue to accelerate. The highest capacity points will be addressed, but also these midrange capacity points.&quot;</p>

<h3>50+ TB HDDs Will Be Here in a Few Years</h3>

<p>Seagate&#39;s launch of its first mass market 30+ TB HAMR hard drives platform will mark a milestone for the company and the whole industry. But apparently the company has another breakthrough to share at this time. The firm said this week that it had created 5 TB platters for 3.5-inch hard drives, which presumably entails new media, new write heads, and new read heads.&nbsp;</p>

<p>&quot;It was nearly four years ago to the day that I first shared our lab results demonstrating 3 TB per disk capacities,&quot; explained Mosley. &quot;And today, we have demonstrated capacities of 5 TB per disk in our recording physics labs.&quot;</p>

<p>For now, these platters are used on spinstands for evaluation and testing purposes, but platters like these will allow for 50 TB HDDs a few years down the line. Seagate&#39;s roadmap indicates that such hard drives will hit the market sometimes in calendar 2026.&nbsp;</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18733/seagate-confirms-30tb-hamr-hdds-in-q3-envisions-50tb-drives-in-a-few-years"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18733/seagate-roadmap-2021-capacities_575px.png" /></a></p>

<p>It is unclear how thin the new platters are. But following current trends of nearline HDD evolution &mdash; increasing areal density and increasing number of platters per hard drive &mdash; it&#39;s not outside the realm of possibility that Seagate will find ways to integrate even more than 10 platters in future drives. In which case Seagate would be able to hit drive sizes even larger than 50 TB.</p>

<p>In any case, with ~3 TB platters in production, samples of ~30 TB HDDs shipping to customers, and 5 TB platters demonstrated in the lab, Seagate&#39;s HAMR roadmap seems to look quite solid. Therefore, expect hard drives to gain capacities rapidly in the coming years.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18733/seagate-confirms-30tb-hamr-hdds-in-q3-envisions-50tb-drives-in-a-few-years</link>
 	<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 18:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18733:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Storage]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>The Intel Core i9-13900KS Review: Taking Intel&#39;s Raptor Lake to 6 GHz</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Back at Intel&#39;s Innovation 2022 event in September, the company let it be known that it had plans to release a &#39;6 GHz&#39; processor based on its Raptor Lake-S series of processors. Though it didn&#39;t come with the same degree of fanfare that Intel&#39;s more imminently launching 13900K/13700K/13600K received, it put enthusiasts and industry watchers on notice that Intel still had one more, even faster Raptor Lake desktop chip waiting in the wings.</p>

<p>Now a few months later, Raptor Lake&#39;s shining moment has arrived. Intel has launched the Intel Core i9-13900KS, a 24-core (8x Perf + 16x Efficiency) part with turbo clock speeds of up to 6 GHz. A mark, which until very recently, was unprecedented without the use of exotic cooling methods such as liquid nitrogen (LN2).&nbsp;</p>

<p>In what is likely to be one of the last in a wide range of Raptor Lake-S SKUs to be announced, Intel has seemingly saved its best for last. The Intel Core i9-13900KS is the faster and unequivocal bigger brother to the Core i9-13900K, with turbo clock speeds of up to 6 GHz while maintaining its halo presence with a 200 MHz increase on both P-core and E-core base frequencies.</p>

<p>Intel&#39;s focus and strategy on delivering halo-level processors in limited supply is something that&#39;s become a regular part of their product stack over the last few years. We&#39;ve previously seen the Core i9-9900KS (Coffee Lake) and i9-12900KS (Alder Lake), which were relative successes in showcasing each Core architecture at their finest point. The Core i9-13900KS looks to follow this trend, although it comes as we&#39;ve reached a time where power efficiency and costs are just a few widely shared concerns globally.</p>

<p>Having the best of the best is somewhat advantageous when there&#39;s a need for cutting-edge desktop performance, but at what cost? Faster cores require more energy, and more energy generates more heat; 6 GHz for the average consumer is finally here, but is it worth taking the plunge? We aim to find out in our review of the 6 GHz Core i9-13900KS.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18728/the-intel-core-i9-13900ks-review-taking-intel-s-raptor-lake-to-6-ghz</link>
 	<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 10:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18728:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Intel Reports Q4 2022 and FY 2022 Earnings: 2022 Goes Out on a Low Note</title>
    <dc:creator>Ryan Smith</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18731/intel-reports-q4-2022-and-fy-2022-earnings-2022-goes-out-on-a-low-note"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18731/Intel_Stock_Q422_575px.png" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Kicking off yet another earnings season, we once again start with Intel. The reigning 800lb gorilla of the chipmaking world is reporting its Q4 2022 and full-year 2022 financial results, closing the book on what has turned an increasingly difficult year for the company. As Intel&rsquo;s primary client and datacenter markets have reached saturation on the back of record sales and spending is slowing for the time being, Intel is seeing significant drops in revenue for both markets. These headwinds, though not unexpected, have broken Intel&rsquo;s 6-year streak of record yearly revenue &ndash; and sent the company back into the red for the most recent quarter.</p>

<p>Starting with quarterly results, for the fourth quarter of 2022, Intel reported $14.0B in revenue, which is a major, 32% decline versus the year-ago quarter. With Intel coming off of what was their best Q4 ever just a year ago, as the saying goes: the higher the highs, the lower the lows. As a result, Q4&rsquo;22 will go down in the books as a money-losing quarter for Intel (on a GAAP basis), with the company losing $661M for the quarter, a 114% decline in net income. Overall, Intel&rsquo;s revenue for the quarter was low end of their already conservative forecasted range.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18731/intel-reports-q4-2022-and-fy-2022-earnings-2022-goes-out-on-a-low-note</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 18:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18731:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Intel NUC 12 Pro Wall Street Canyon Kits Review: Alder Lake in UCFF Avatar</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Intel introduced the ultra-compact form-factor in 2012 to reinvigorate the PC market. The incredible success of the product line has now resulted in the brand name propagating to other novel system configurations and form factors. The introduction of the mainstream Alder Lake NUCs last year - the NUC 12 Pro (Wall Street Canyon) - marked a decade-long journey for the original design. As part of bringing out the versatility of the form-factor and its evolution over the last ten years, Intel sampled three top-end Wall Street Canyon NUCs targeting different market segments - the NUC12WSKi7 for traditional business and consumer users, the NUC12WSKv7 in a slightly more eye-catching designer chassis for business and enterprise deployments, and the NUC12WSBi70Z in a rugged fanless case for IoT / Edge applications in industrial environments. Read on for a comprehensive analysis of the mainstream NUC 12 Pro mini-PC platform.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18729/intel-nuc-12-pro-wall-street-canyon-kits-review-alder-lake-in-ucff-avatar</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 11:30:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18729:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Systems]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>SK hynix Intros LPDDR5T Memory: Low Power RAM at up to 9.6Gbps</title>
    <dc:creator>Ryan Smith</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18730/sk-hynix-intros-lpddr5t-memory-low-power-ram-at-up-to-96gbps"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18730/SK-hynix_LPDDR5T_02_crop_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>In a bit of a surprise move, SK hynix this week has announced a new variation of LPDDR5 memory technology, which they are calling LPDDR5T. Low Power Double Data Rate 5 Turbo (LPDDR5T) further ramps up the clockspeeds for LPDDR5-type memory, with SK hynix stating that their new memory will be able to clock at high as 9.6Gbps/pin, 13% faster than their top-bin 8.5Gbps LPDDR5X. According to the company, the memory is sampling now to partners as a 16GB part, with mass production set to begin in the second half of this year.</p>

<p>SK hynix is positioning LPDDR5T as an interim memory technology to cover the gap between <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/16851/jedec-announces-lpddr5x-at-up-to-8533mbps">LPDDR5X</a> and the future development of LPDDR6, offering what amounts to a half-step up in memory bandwidth for customers who would like something faster than what contemporary LPDDR5X memory is capable of. That standard, as it currently stands, only goes to 8533Mbps, so any LPDDR5-type memory clocked higher than that is technically outside of the official JEDEC specification. Still, SK hynix&rsquo;s announcement comes a bit unexpectedly, as while it&rsquo;s not unusual for memory manufacturers to announce new technologies ahead of the industry&rsquo;s standardization body, there hadn&rsquo;t been any previous chatter of anyone coming to market with a further evolution of LPDDR5.</p>

<p>At this point the technical details on the new memory are limited. SK hynix was able to confirm that LPDDR5T will operate at the same voltages as LPDDR5X, with a VDD voltage range of 1.01v to 1.12v (nominally 1.05v) and a VDDQ of 0.5v. Coupled with that, as previously mentioned the new memory will max out at a data rate of 9.6Gbps/pin, which for a 64-bit part would mean a full data rate of 76.8GB/second. Otherwise, at this point all outward appearances are that LPDDR5T is just higher clocked LPDDR5X, given a new name since its data rate is outside the scope of LPDDR5X.</p>

<table align="center" border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="1" width="680">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td align="center" colspan="7">LPDDR Generations</td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td width="200">&nbsp;</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="225"><small>LPDDR4</small></td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="225"><small>LPDDR4X</small></td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="225"><small>LPDDR5</small></td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="225"><small>LPDDR5X</small></td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="225"><small>LPDDR5T<br />
			(Provisional)</small></td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Max Density</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">64 Gbit</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">32 Gbit</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">32 Gbit?</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Max Data Rate</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">4266Mbps</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">6400Mbps</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">8533Mbps</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">9600Mbps</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Channels</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">2</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">1</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">4?</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Width</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" valign="middle">x32 (2x x16)</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" valign="middle">x16</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">x64</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Banks<br />
			(Per Channel)</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">8</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">8-16</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="middle">16?</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Bank Grouping</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" valign="middle">No</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" valign="middle">Yes</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">Yes?</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Prefetch</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">16n</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">16n</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">16n?</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Voltage</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle">1.1v</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle"><em>Variable</em><br />
			Nominal: 1.05v<br />
			Max: 1.1v</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle"><em>Variable</em><br />
			Nominal: 1.05v<br />
			Max: 1.12v</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Vddq</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">1.1v</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" valign="middle">0.6v</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="middle">0.5v</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>But whatever LPDDR5T is (or isn&rsquo;t), SK hynix tells us that they intend to make a proper JEDEC standard of it. The company is already working with JEDEC on standardization of the memory technology, and while this doesn&rsquo;t guarantee that other memory vendors will pick up the spec, it&rsquo;s a sign that LPDDR5T isn&rsquo;t going to be some niche memory technology that only ends up in a few products. This also means that the rest of the pertinent technical details should be published in the none too distant future.</p>

<p>In the meantime, for their initial LPDDR5T parts, SK hynix is going to be shipping a multi-die chip in a x64 configuration. According to the company&rsquo;s PR office, they&rsquo;re producing both 12Gb and 16Gb dies, so there&rsquo;s a potential range of options for package densities, with the 16GB (128Gbit) package being the largest configuration. All of this RAM, in turn, is being built on the company&rsquo;s 1<em>a</em>nm process, which is their fourth-generation 10nm process using EUV, and paired with High-K metal gates (HKMG).</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18730/sk-hynix-intros-lpddr5t-memory-low-power-ram-at-up-to-96gbps"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18730/SK-hynix_LPDDR5T_01_crop_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>SK hynix&rsquo;s decision to go with only a x64 package out of the gate is a notable one, since these higher density packages are typically limited to use in high-end smartphones and other high-performance devices (laptops, servers, etc), underscoring the intended market. For their part, SK hynix has stated that they expect the application of LPDDR5T to &ldquo;expand beyond smartphones to artificial intelligence (AI), machine learning and augmented/virtual reality (AR/VR)&rdquo;. LPDDR memory has been seeing increasing use in non-mobile products, so this doesn&rsquo;t come as a surprise given the high-end nature of the technology. Server hardware vendors in particular come to mind as potential customers, since those products can easily absorb any increased power consumption from the higher memory clockspeeds.</p>

<p>Wrapping things up, SK hynix says that they expect to begin mass production of LPDDR5T in the second half of this year. So depending on just when in the year that production begins, and when their downstream customers implement the new RAM, it could begin showing up in products as easy as the end of this year.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18730/sk-hynix-intros-lpddr5t-memory-low-power-ram-at-up-to-96gbps</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 10:30:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18730:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Memory]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>ASRock DeskMeet B660 Review: An Affordable NUC Extreme?</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>ASRock was one of the earliest vendors to cater to the small-form factor (SFF) PC market with a host of custom-sized motherboards based on notebook platforms. Despite missing the NUC bus for the most part, they have been quite committed to the 5x5 mini-STX form-factor introduced in 2015. ASRock&#39;s DeskMini lineup is based on mSTX boards and has both Intel and AMD options for the end-user. While allowing for installation of socketed processors, the form-factor could not support a discrete GPU slot. Around 2018, Intel started making a push towards equipping some of their NUC models with user-replaceable discrete GPUs. In order to gain some market share in that segment, ASRock introduced their DeskMeet product line early last year with support for socketed processors and a PCIe x16 slot for installing add-in cards. Read on for a detailed analysis of the features, performance, and value proposition of the DeskMeet B660 - a 8L SFF PC based on the Intel B660 chipset, capable of accommodating Alder Lake or Raptor Lake CPUs.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18706/asrock-deskmeet-b660-review-an-affordable-nuc-extreme</link>
 	<pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 08:30:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18706:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Systems]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>The FSP Hydro G Pro 1000W ATX 3.0 PSU Review: Solid and Affordable ATX 3.0</title>
    <dc:creator>E. Fylladitakis</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>With the ATX 3.0 era now well underway, we&#39;ve been taking a look at the first generation of ATX 3.0 power supplies to hit the market. Introducing the 16-pin 12VHPWR connector, which can supply up to 600 Watts of power to PCIe cards, ATX 3.0 marks the start of what will be a slow shift in the market. As high-end video cards continue to grow in power consumption, power supply manufacturers are working to catch up with these trends with a new generation of PSUs &ndash; not only updating power supplies to meet the peak energy demands of the latest cards, but also to better handle the large swings in power consumption that these cards incur.</p>

<p>For our second ATX 3.0 power supply, we&#39;re looking at a unit from FSP Group, the Hydro G Pro ATX 3.0. Unlike some of the other ATX 3.0 PSUs we&#39;ve looked at (and will be looking at), FSP has taken a slightly different approach with their first ATX 3.0 unit: rather than modifying its best platform or releasing a new top-tier platform, FSP went with an upgrade of its most popular platform, the original Hydro G Pro. As such, the new Hydro G Pro ATX 3.0 1000W PSU doesn&#39;t have especially impressive specifications on paper, but it boasts good all-around performance for an affordable price tag ($199 MSRP). That makes FSP&#39;s platform notable at a time when most ATX 3.0 come with an early adopter tax, with FSP clearly aiming to entice mainstream users who may not currently need an ATX 3.0 PSU but would like to own one in case of future upgrades.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18697/the-fsp-hydro-g-pro-1000w-atx-30-psu-review</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 08:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18697:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Cases/Cooling/PSUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>TSMC&#39;s 3nm Journey: Slow Ramp, Huge Investments, Big Future</title>
    <dc:creator>Anton Shilov</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18727/tsmcs-3nm-journey-slow-ramp-huge-investments-big-future"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18727/tsmc_semiconductor_fab14_production_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Last week, TSMC issued their Q4 and full-year 2022 earnings reports for the company. Besides confirming that TSMC was closing out a very busy, very profitable year for the world&#39;s top chip fab&nbsp;&ndash; booking almost $34 billion in net income for the year&nbsp;&ndash; the end-of-year report from the company has also given us a fresh update on the state of TSMC&#39;s various fab projects.</p>

<p>The big news coming out of TSMC for Q4&#39;22 is that TSMC has initiated high volume manufacturing of chips on its N3 (3nm-class) fabrication technology. The ramp of this node will be rather slow initially due to high design costs and the complexities of the first N3B implementation of the node, so the world&#39;s largest foundry does not expect it to be a significant contributor to its revenue in 2023. Yet, the firm will invest tens of billions of dollars in expanding its N3-capable manufacturing capacity as eventually&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17452/tsmc-readies-five-3nm-process-technologies-with-finflex">N3 is expected to become a popular long-lasting family of production nodes</a> for TSMC.</p>

<h3>Slow Ramp Initially</h3>

<p>&quot;Our N3 has successfully entered volume production in late fourth quarter last year as planned, with good yield,&quot; said C. C. Wei, chief executive of TSMC. &quot;We expect a smooth ramp in 2023 driven by both HPC and smartphone applications. As our customers&#39; demand for N3 exceeds our ability to supply, we expect the N3 to be fully utilized in 2023.&quot;</p>

<p>Keeping in mind that TSMC&#39;s capital expenditures in 2021 and 2022 were focused mostly on expanding its N5 (5nm-class) manufacturing capacities, it is not surprising that the company&#39;s N3-capable capacity is modest. Meanwhile, TSMC does not expect N3 to account for any sizable share of its revenue before Q3.</p>

<p>In fact, the No. 1 foundry expects N3 nodes (which include both baseline N3 and relaxed N3E that is set to enter HVM in the second half of 2023) to account for maybe 4% - 6% of the company&#39;s wafer revenue in 2023. And yet this would exceed the contribution of N5 in its first two quarters of HVM in 2020 (which was about $3.5 billion).</p>

<p>&quot;We expect [sizable N3 revenue contribution] to start in third quarter 2023 and N3 will&nbsp;contribute mid-single-digit percentage of our total wafer revenue in 2023,&quot; said Wei. &quot;We expect the N3 revenue in 2023 to be higher than N5 revenue in its first year in 2020.&quot;</p>

<p>Many analysts believe that the baseline N3 (also known as N3B) will be used by Apple either exclusively or almost exclusively, which is TSMC&#39;s largest customer that is willing to adopt leading-edge nodes ahead of all other companies, despite high initial costs. If this assumption is correct and Apple is indeed the primary customer to use baseline N3, then it is noteworthy that TSMC mentions both smartphone and HPC (a vague term that TSMC uses to describe virtually all ASICs, CPUs, GPUs, SoCs, and FPGAs not aimed at automotive, communications, and smartphones) applications in conjunction with N3 in 2023.&nbsp;</p>

<h3>N3E Coming in the Second Half</h3>

<p>One of the reasons why many companies are waiting for TSMC&#39;s relaxed N3E technology (which is entering HVM in the second half of 2023, according to TSMC) is the higher performance and power improvements, as well as even more aggressive logic scaling. Another is that the process will offer lower costs, albeit at the cost of a <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/no-sram-scaling-implies-on-more-expensive-cpus-and-gpus">lack of SRAM scaling compared to N5</a>, according to analysts from&nbsp;<a href="https://www.chinarenaissance.com/">China Renaissance</a>.</p>

<p>&quot;N3E, with six fewer EUV layers than the baseline N3, promises simpler process complexity, intrinsic cost and manufacturing cycle time, albeit with less density gain,&quot; Szeho Ng, an analyst with China Renaissance, wrote in a note to clients this week.&nbsp;</p>

<table align="center" border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="1" width="680">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td align="center" colspan="4">Advertised PPA Improvements of New Process Technologies<br />
			<small>Data announced during conference calls, events, press briefings and press releases</small></td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td rowspan="2" width="186">&nbsp;</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="middle" width="137">TSMC</td>
		</tr>
		<tr class="tlblue">
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="136">N3<br />
			vs<br />
			N5</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle" width="136">N3E<br />
			vs<br />
			N5</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Power</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">-25-30%</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">-34%</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Performance</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">+10-15%</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">+18%</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Logic Area<br />
			<br />
			Reduction* %<br />
			<br />
			Logic Density*</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">0.58x<br />
			<br />
			-42%<br />
			<br />
			1.7x</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">0.625x<br />
			<br />
			-37.5%<br />
			<br />
			1.6x</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">SRAM Cell Size</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">0.0199&micro;m&sup2; (-5% vs N5)</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">0.021&micro;m&sup2; (same as N5)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey">Volume<br />
			Manufacturing</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">Late 2022</td>
			<td align="center" valign="middle">H2 2023</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>Ho says that TSMC&#39;s original N3 features up to 25 EUV layers and can apply multi-patterning for some of them for additional density. By contract, N3E supports up to 19 EUV layers and only uses single-patterning EUV, which reduces complexity, but also means lower density.</p>

<p>&quot;Clients&#39; interest in the optimized N3E (post the baseline N3B ramp-up, which is largely limited to Apple) is high, embracing compute-intensive applications in HPC (AMD, Intel), mobile (Qualcomm, Mediatek) and ASICs (Broadcom, Marvell),&quot; wrote Ho.</p>

<p>It looks like N3E will indeed be TSMC&#39;s main 3nm-class working horse before N3P, N3S, and N3X arrive later on.</p>

<h3>Tens of Billions on N3</h3>

<p>While TSMC&#39;s 3nm-class nodes are going to earn the company a little more than $4 billion in 2023, the company will spend tens of billions of dollars expanding its fab capacity to produce chips on various N3 nodes. This year the company&#39;s capital expenditures are guided to be between $32 billion - $36 billion. 70% of that sum will be used on advanced process technologies (N7 and below), which includes N3-capable capacity in Taiwan, as well as equipment for Fab 21 in Arizona (N4, N5 nodes). Meanwhile 20% will be used for fabs producing chips on specialty technologies (which essentially means a variety of 28nm-class processes), and 10% will be spent on things like advanced packaging and mask production.</p>

<p>Spending at least $22 billion on N3 and N5 capacity indicates that TSMC is confident on the demand for these nodes. And there is a good reason for that: the N3 family of process technologies is set to be TSMC&#39;s last FinFET-based family of production nodes for complex high-performance chips. The company&#39;s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17453/tsmc-unveils-n2-nanosheets-bring-significant-benefits">N2 (2nm-class) manufacturing process</a>&nbsp;will rely on nanosheet-based gate-all-around field-effect transistors (GAAFETs). In fact, analyst Szeho Ng from China Renaissance believes that a significant share of this year&#39;s CapEx set for advanced technologies will be spent on N3 capacity, setting the ground for roll-out of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17452/tsmc-readies-five-3nm-process-technologies-with-finflex">N3E, N3P, N3X, and N3S</a>. Since N3-capable fabs can also produce chips on N5 processes, TSMC will be able to use this capacity where there will be significant demand for N5-based chips as well.</p>

<p>&quot;TSMC guided 2023 CapEx&nbsp;at $32-36bn (2022: US$36.3bn), with its expansion focused on N3 in Fab 18 (Tainan),&quot; the analyst wrote in a note to clients.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Since TSMC&#39;s N2 process technology will only ramp starting in 2026, N3 will indeed be a long lasting node for the company. Furthermore, since it will be the last FinFET-based node for advanced chips, it will be used for many years to come as not all applications will need GAAFETs.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18727/tsmcs-3nm-journey-slow-ramp-huge-investments-big-future</link>
 	<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 09:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18727:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Semiconductors]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Intel Unveils Core i9-13900KS: Raptor Lake Spreads Its Wings to 6.0 GHz</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>Initially teased&nbsp;by Intel CEO Pat Gelsinger during their Innovation 2022 opening keynote, Intel has unveiled its highly anticipated&nbsp;6 GHz out-of-the-box processor, the Core i9-13900KS. The Core i9-13900KS is a special, highly clocked bin of the regular i9-13900K, offering the same 24-core (8P+16E) hybrid architecture, but with an impressive&nbsp;P-core maximum turbo clockspeed of up to 6&nbsp;GHz.</p>

<p>Based on Intel&#39;s existing Raptor Lake-S desktop silicon, Intel claims that the&nbsp;Core i9-13900KS is the first desktop processor to reach 6 GHz out&nbsp;of the box without overclocking. With normal chips hitting up to 5.8GHz, the i9-13900KS is an even more extreme bin of that silicon, with Intel identifying chips that can run even harder to make it to 6 GHz. The trade-off for this extra burst of performance is that the power consumption of the chip is even higher than Intel&#39;s usual high-end desktop parts, with an official TDP of 150 Watts, and an &quot;extreme&quot; power profile that goes as high as 320 Watts under load.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, unlike most Intel CPU launches, the company is wasting no time on bringing their new special edition chip to market: the $699 CPU is available immediately.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18726/intel-unveils-core-i9-13900ks-raptor-lake-spreads-its-wings-to-6-0-ghz</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 09:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18726:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>Micron Launches 9400 NVMe Series: U.3 SSDs for Data Center Workloads</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18725/micron-launches-9400-nvme-series-u3-ssds-for-data-center-workloads"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18725/micron-9400-carousel_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Micron is taking the wraps off their latest data center SSD offering today. The 9400 NVMe Series builds upon Micron&#39;s success with their third-generation 9300 series <a href="https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-introduces-new-series-high-performance-nvme-ssds-cloud">introduced</a> back in Q2 2019. The 9300 series had adopted the U.2 form-factor with a PCIe 3.0 x4 interface, and utilized their 64L 3D TLC NAND. With a maximum capacity of 15.36 TB, the drive matched the highest-capacity HDDs on the storage amount front at that time (obviously with much higher performance numbers). In the past couple of years, the data center has moved towards PCIe 4.0 and U.3 in a bid to keep up with performance requirements and unify NVMe, SAS, and SATA support. Keeping these in mind, Micron is releasing the 9400 NVMe series of U.3 SSDs with a PCIe 4.0 x4 interface using their now-mature 176L 3D TLC NAND. Increased capacity per die is also now enabling Micron to present 2.5&quot; U.3 drives with capacities up to 30.72 TB, effectively doubling capacity per rack over the previous generation.</p>

<p>Similar to the 9300 NVMe series, the 9400 NVMe series is also optimized for data-intensive workloads and comes in two versions - the 9400 PRO and 9400 MAX. The Micron 9400 PRO is optimized for read-intensive workloads (1 DWPD), while the Micron 9400 MAX is meant for mixed use (3 DWPD). The maximum capacity points are 30.72 TB and 25.60 TB respectively. The specifications of the two drive families are summarized in the table below.</p>

<table border="1" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td align="center" colspan="4" style="vertical-align: middle;">Micron 9400 NVMe Enterprise SSDs</td>
		</tr>
		<tr align="center" class="tlblue">
			<td colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">&nbsp;</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">9400 PRO</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">9400 MAX</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Form Factor</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">U.3 2.5&quot; 15mm</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Interface</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">PCIe 4.0 NVMe 1.4</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Capacities</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">7.68TB<br />
			15.36TB<br />
			30.72</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">6.4TB<br />
			12.8TB<br />
			25.6TB</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">NAND</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Micron 176L 3D TLC</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Sequential Read</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">7000 MBps</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Sequential Write</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">7000 MBps</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Random Read (4 KB)</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">1.6M IOPS (7.68TB and 15.36TB)<br />
			1.5M IOPS (30.72TB)</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">1.6M IOPS (6.4TB and 12.8TB)<br />
			1.5M IOPS (25.6TB)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Random Write (4 KB)</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">300K IOPS</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">600K IOPS (6.4TB and 12.8TB)<br />
			550K IOPS (25.6TB)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Power</td>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle;">Operating</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">14-21 W (7.68TB)<br />
			16-25W (15.36TB)<br />
			17-25W (30.72TB)</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">14-21 W (6.40TB)<br />
			16-24W (12.8TB)<br />
			17-25W (25.6TB)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" style="vertical-align: middle;">Idle</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">? W</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">? W</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Write Endurance</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">1 DWPD</td>
			<td align="center" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">3 DWPD</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="2" style="vertical-align: middle;">Warranty</td>
			<td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">5 years</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>The 9400 NVMe SSD series is already in volume production for AI / ML and other HPC workloads. The move to a faster interface, as well as higher-performance NAND enables a 77% improvement in random IOPS per watt over the previous generation. Micron is also claiming better all round performance across a variety of workloads compared to enterprise SSDs from competitors.</p>

<p>The Micron 9400 PRO goes against the Solidigm D7-5520, Samsung PM1733, and the Kioxia CM6-R. The Solidigm D7-5520 is handicapped by lower capacity points (due to its use of 144L TLC), resulting in lower performance against the 9400 PRO in all but the sequential reads numbers. The Samsung PM1733 also tops out at 15.36TB with performance numbers similar to that of the Solidigm model. The Kioxia CM6-R is the only other U.3 SSD with capacities up to 30.72TB. However, its performance numbers across all corners lags well behind the 9400 PRO&#39;s.</p>

<p>The Micron 9400 MAX has competition from the Solidigm D7-P5620, Samsung PM1735, and the Kioxia CM6-V. Except for sequential reads, the Solidigm D7-P5620 lags the 9400 MAX in performance as well as capacity points. The PM1735 is only available in an HHHL AIC form-factor and uses PCIe 4.0 x8 interface. So, despite its 8 GBps sequential read performance, it can&#39;t be deployed in a manner similar to that of the 9400 MAX. The Kioxia CM6-V tops out at 12.8TB and has lower performance numbers compared to the 9400 MAX.</p>

<p>Despite not being the first to launch 32TB-class SSDs into the data center market, Micron has ensured that their eventual offering provides top-tier performance across a variety of workloads compared to the competition. We hope to present some hands-on performance numbers for the SSD in the coming weeks.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18725/micron-launches-9400-nvme-series-u3-ssds-for-data-center-workloads</link>
 	<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 09:20:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18725:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ SSDs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>The AMD Ryzen 9 7900, Ryzen 7 7700, and Ryzen 5 7600 Review: Zen 4 Efficiency at 65 Watts</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>In Q3 of last year, AMD released the first CPUs based on its highly anticipated Zen 4 architecture. Not only did their Ryzen 7000 parts raise the bar in terms of performance compared with the previous Ryzen 5000 series, but it also gave birth to AMD&#39;s latest platform, AM5. Some of the most significant benefits of Zen 4 and the AM5 platform include support for PCIe 5.0, DDR5 memory, and access to the latest and greatest&nbsp;of what&#39;s available in controller sets.&nbsp;</p>

<p>While the competition at the higher end of the x86 processor market is a metaphorical firefight with heavy weaponry, AMD has struggled to offer users on tighter budgets anything to sink their teeth into. It&#39;s clear Zen 4 is a powerful and highly efficient architecture, but with the added cost of DDR5, finding all of the components to fit under tighter budget constraints with AM5 isn&#39;t as easy as it once was on AM4.</p>

<p>AMD has launched three new processors designed to offer users on a budget something to get their money&#39;s worth, with performance that make them favorable for users looking for Zen 4 hardware but without the hefty financial outlay. The AMD Ryzen 9 7900, Ryzen 7 7700, and Ryzen 5 7600 processors all feature the Zen 4 microarchitecture and come with a TDP of just 65 W, which makes them viable for all kinds of users, such as enthusiasts looking for a more affordable entry-point onto the AM5 platform.</p>

<p>Of particular interest is AMD&#39;s new budget offering for the Ryzen 7000 series: the Ryzen 5 7600, which offers six cores/twelve threads for&nbsp;entry-level builders looking to build a system with all of the features of AM5 and the Ryzen 7000 family, but at a much more affordable price point.&nbsp;We are looking at all three of AMD&#39;s new Ryzen 7000 65 W TDP processors to see how they stack up against the competition, to see if AMD&#39;s lower-powered, lower-priced non-X variants can offer anything in the way of value for consumers. We also aim to see if AMD&#39;s&nbsp;65 W TDP implementation can shine on&nbsp;TSMC&#39;s 5 nm node process with performance per watt efficiency that AMD claims is the best on the market.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18693/the-amd-ryzen-9-7900-ryzen-7-7700-and-ryzen-5-5-7600-review-ryzen-7000-at-65-w-zen-4-efficiency</link>
 	<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 09:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18693:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>CES 2023: QNAP Brings Hybrid Processors and E1.S SSD Support to the NAS Market</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18724/ces-2023-qnap-brings-hybrid-processors-and-e1s-ssd-support-to-the-nas-market"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18724/carousel_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Over the last few years, the developments in the commercial off-the-shelf (COTS) network-attached storage (NAS) market have mostly been on the software front - bringing in more business-oriented value additions and better support for containers and virtual machines. We have had hardware updates in terms of processor choices and inclusion of M.2 SSD slots (primarily for SSD caching), but they have not been revolutionary changes.</p>

<p>At CES 2023, QNAP revealed plans for two different NAS units - the all-flash TBS-574X (based on the Intel Alder Lake-P platform), and the ML-focused TS-AI642 (based on the Rockchip RK3588 app processor). While QNAP only provided a teaser of the capabilities, there are a couple of points worth talking about to get an idea of where the COTS NAS market is headed towards in the near future.</p>

<h3>Hybrid Processors</h3>

<p>Network-Attached storage units have typically been based on either server platforms in the SMB / SME space or single-board computer (SBC) platforms in the home consumer / SOHO space. Traditionally, both platforms have eschewed big.LITTLE / hybrid processors for a variety of reasons. In the x86 space, we saw hybrid processors entering the mainstream market recently with Intel&#39;s Alder Lake family. In the ARM world, big.LITTLE has been around for a relatively longer time. However, server workloads are typically unsuitable for that type of architecture. Without a credible use-case for such processors, it is also unlikely that servers will go that route. However, SBCs are a different case, and we have seen a number of application processors adopting the big.LITTLE strategy getting used in that market segment.</p>

<p>Both the all-flash TBS-574X and the AI NAS TS-AI642 are based on hybrid processors. The TBS-574X uses the <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/sku/226257/intel-core-i31220p-processor-12m-cache-up-to-4-40-ghz/specifications.html">Intel Core i3-1220P</a> (Alder Lake-P) in a 2P + 8E configuration. The TS-AI642 is based on the Rockchip RK3588 [ <a href="https://www.rock-chips.com/uploads/pdf/2022.8.26/192/RK3588%20Brief%20Datasheet.pdf">PDF</a> ], with 4x Cortex-A76 and 4x Cortex-A55 fabricated in Samsung&#39;s 8LPP process.</p>

<p>QNAP is no stranger to marketing Atom-based NAS units with 2.5 GbE support - their recent <a href="https://www.qnap.com/en-us/product/compare?products=ts-264%2Cts-464%2Cts-664&amp;ref=product_overview">Jasper Lake-based tower NAS line-up</a> has proved extremely popular for SOHO / SMB use-cases. The Gracemont cores in the Core i3-1220P are going to be a step-up in performance, and the addition of two performance cores can easily help with user experience related to features more amenable for use in their Core-based units.</p>

<p>NAS units have become powerful enough to move above and beyond their basic file serving / backup target functionality. The QTS applications curated by QNAP help in providing well-integrated value additions. Some of the most popular ones enable container support as well as the ability to run virtual machines. As the range of workloads run on the NAS simultaneously start to vary, hybrid processors can pitch in to improve performance while maintaining power efficiency.</p>

<p>On the AI NAS front, the Rockchip RK3588 has processor cores powerful enough for a multi-bay NAS. However, QNAP is putting more focus on the neural network accelerator blocks (the SoC has 6 TOPS of NN inference performance), allowing the NAS to be marketed to heavy users of their surveillance and &#39;AI&#39; apps such as <a href="https://www.qnap.com/go/solution/qvr-face/">QVR Face</a> (for face recognition in surveillance videos), <a href="https://www.qnap.com/go/software/qvr-smart-search">QVR Smart Search</a> (for event searching in surveillance videos), and <a href="https://www.qnap.com/go/software/qumagie">QuMagie</a> (for easily indexed photo albums with &#39;AI&#39; functionality).</p>

<h3>E1.S Hot-Swappable SSDs</h3>

<p>QNAP&#39;s first NASbook - an all-flash NAS using M.2 SSDs - was introduced into the market last year. The <a href="https://www.qnap.com/en-us/product/tbs-464">TBS-464</a> remains a unique product in the market, but goes against the NAS concept of hot-swappable drives.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18724/ces-2023-qnap-brings-hybrid-processors-and-e1s-ssd-support-to-the-nas-market"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18724/tbs-464_575px.jpg" /></a><br />
<i>QNAP&#39;s First-Generation NASbook - the TBS-464</i></p>

<p>At the time of its introduction, there was no industry standard for hot-swappable NVMe flash drives suitable for the NASbook&#39;s form-factor. U.2 and U.3 drive slots with hot-swapping capabilities did exist in rackmount units meant for enterprises and datacenters. So, QNAP&#39;s NASbook was launched without hot-swapping support. Meanwhile, the industry was consolidating towards E1.S and E1.L as <a href="https://www.snia.org/forums/cmsi/knowledge/formfactors">standard form-factors</a> for hot-swappable NVMe storage.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18724/ces-2023-qnap-brings-hybrid-processors-and-e1s-ssd-support-to-the-nas-market"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18724/e1s-mod_575px.png" /></a><br />
<i>(L to R) E1.S 5.9mm (courtesy of SMART Modular Systems); E1.S Symmetric Enclosure (courtesy of Intel); E1.S (courtesy of KIOXIA)</i></p>

<p>QNAP&#39;s 2023 NASbook - the TBS-574X - will be the first QNAP NAS to support E1.S hot-swappable SSDs (up to 15mm in thickness). In order to increase drive compatibility, QNAP will also be bundling M.2 adapters attached to each drive bay. This will allow end-users to use M.2 SSDs in the NASbook while market availability of E1.S SSDs expands.</p>

<h3>Specifications Summary</h3>

<p>The TBS-574X uses the Intel Core i3-1220P (2P + 8E - 10C/12T) and includes 16GB of DDR4 RAM. Memory expansion support is not clear as yet (It is likely that these are DDR4 SO-DIMMs). There are five drive bays, and the NAS seems to be running QTS based on QNAP&#39;s model naming). The NASbook also sports 2.5 GbE and 10 GbE ports, two USB4 ports (likely Thunderbolt 4 sans certification, as QNAP claims 40 Gbps support, and ADL-P supports it natively), and 4K HDMI output. The NASbook also supports video transcoding with the integrated GPU in the Core i3-1220P. QNAP is primarily targeting collaborative video editing use-cases with the TBS-574X.</p>

<p>The TS-AI642 uses the RockChip RK3588 (4x CA-76 + 4x CA-55) app processor. The RAM specifications were not provided - SoC specs indicate LPDDR4, but we have reached out to QNAP for the exact amount . There are six drive bays. This is again interesting, since the SoC natively offers only up to 3 SATA ports. So, QNAP is either using a port multiplier or a separate SATA controller connected to the PCIe lanes for this purpose. The SoC&#39;s native network support is restricted to dual GbE ports, but QNAP is including 2.5 GbE as well as a PCIe Gen 3 slot for 10 GbE expansion. These are also bound to take up the limited number of PCIe lanes in the processor (which is 4x PCIe 3.0, configurable as 1 x4, or 2 x2, or 4 x1). Overall, the hardware is quite interesting in terms of how QNAP will be able to manage performance expectations with the SoC&#39;s capabilities. With a focus on surveillance deployments and cloud storage integration, the performance may be good enough even with port multipliers.</p>

<h3>Concluding Remarks</h3>

<p>Overall, QNAP&#39;s teaser of their two upcoming desktop NAS products has provided us with insights into where the NAS market for SOHOs / SMBs is headed in the near future. QNAP has never shied away from exploring new hardware options, unlike Synology, QSAN, Terramaster, and the like. While we are very bullish on E1.S support and hybrid processors in desktop NAS units, the appeal of the RockChip-based AI NAS may depend heavily on its price to capabilities / performance aspect.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18724/ces-2023-qnap-brings-hybrid-processors-and-e1s-ssd-support-to-the-nas-market</link>
 	<pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 08:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18724:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Trade Shows]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>A Lighter Touch: Exploring CPU Power Scaling On Core i9-13900K and Ryzen 9 7950X</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>One of the biggest running gags on&nbsp;social media and Reddit is how hot and power hungry CPUs have become over the years. Whereas at one time flagship x86 CPUs didn&#39;t even require a heatsink, they can now saturate whole radiators. Thankfully, it&#39;s not quite to the levels of a nuclear reactor, as the memes go&nbsp;&ndash; but as the kids say these days, it&#39;s also not a <em>nothingburger</em>. Designing for higher TDPs and greater power consumption has allowed chipmakers to keep pushing the envelope in terms of performance &ndash; something that&#39;s no easy feat in a post-Dennard world &ndash; but it&#39;s certainly created some new headaches regarding power consumption and heat in the process. Something that, for better or worse, the latest flagship chips from both AMD and Intel exemplify.</p>

<p>But despite these general trends, this doesn&#39;t mean that a high performance desktop CPU also needs to be a power hog. In our review of AMD&#39;s Ryzen 9 7950X, our testing showed that even capped at a these days pedestrian 65 Watts, the 7950X could deliver a significant amount of performance at less than half its normal power consumption.</p>

<p>If you&#39;ll pardon the pun, power efficiency has become a hot talking point these days, as enthusiasts look to save on their energy bills (especially in Europe) while still enjoying fast CPU performance, looking for other ways to take advantage of the full silicon capabilities of AMD&#39;s Raphael and Intel&#39;s Raptor Lake-S platforms besides stuffing the chips with as many joules as possible. All the while, the small form factor market remains a steadfast outpost for high efficiency chips, where cooler chips are critical for building smaller and more compact systems that can forego the need for large cooling systems.</p>

<p>All of this is to say that while it&#39;s great to see the envelope pushed in terms of peak performance, the typical focus on how an unlocked chip scales when overclocking (pushing CPU frequency and CPU VCore voltages) is just one way to look at overall CPU performance. So today we are&nbsp;going to go the other way, and to take a look at overall energy efficiency for users &ndash; to see what happens when we aim for the sweet spot on the voltage/frequency curve. To that end, today we&#39;re investigating how the Intel Core i9-13900K and AMD Ryzen 9 7950X perform at different power levels, and to see what kind of benefits power scaling can provide compared to stock settings.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/17641/lighter-touch-cpu-power-scaling-13900k-7950x</link>
 	<pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 08:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,17641:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>CES 2023: Akasa Introduces Fanless Cases for Wall Street Canyon NUCs</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/carousel_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Akasa is one of the very few vendors to carry a portfolio of passively-cooled chassis solutions for the Intel NUCs. We had reviewed their <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/16191/akasa-turing-fanless-case-review-noiseless-nuc-nonpareil">Turing solution with the Bean Cayon NUC</a> and the <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17502/intel-nuc11tnbi5-and-akasa-newton-tn-fanless-case-review-silencing-the-tiger">Newton TN with the Tiger Canyon NUC</a>, and come away impressed with the performance of both cases. At CES 2023, the company is upgrading their portfolio of fanless NUC cases to support the mainstream NUC Pro using the 12<sup>th</sup>-Gen Core processors - the <a href="https://ark.intel.com/content/www/us/en/ark/products/codename/225823/products-formerly-wall-street-canyon.html">Wall Street Canyon</a>.</p>

<h3>Turing WS</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/update.php?tpl=product/product.detail.tpl&amp;type=FANLESS%20CASES&amp;type_sub=Intel%20NUC&amp;model=A-NUC87-M1B">Turing WS</a> builds upon the original Turing chassis to accommodate the updated I/Os of the Wall Street Canyon NUC.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/turing-ws-01_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The 2.7L chassis can be oriented either horizontally or vertically, and retains the ability to install a 2.5&quot; SATA drive. Improvements over the previous generations include the inclusion of an updated thermal solution for the M.2 SSD.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/turing-m2-thermal_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/turing-ws-ports_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The Turing WS retains all the I/Os of the regular Wall Street Canyon kits and also includes antenna holes for those requiring Wi-Fi connection in the system. The company does offer suggested complementary additions to the build for that purpose - a <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/search.php?seed=A-ATN01-BK">tri-band Wi-Fi antenna</a> and corresponding <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/update.php?tpl=product/product.detail.tpl&amp;model=A-ATC01-150GR">pigtails</a>. We would like to see these getting included by default for the DIY versions of the Turing WS that get sold in retail.</p>

<h3>Newton WS</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/update.php?tpl=product/product.detail.tpl&amp;type=FANLESS%20CASES&amp;type_sub=Intel%20NUC&amp;model=A-NUC92-M1B">Newton WS</a> is a minor update to the Newton TN that we <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17502/intel-nuc11tnbi5-and-akasa-newton-tn-fanless-case-review-silencing-the-tiger">reviewed</a> last year.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/newton-ws-01_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The key change is the removal of the serial cable and corresponding rear I/O cut-out. In fact, Akasa indicates that the Newton TN can also be used with the Wall Street Canyon for consumers requiring the serial I/O support.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/newton-ws-02_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The 1.9L volume, additional USB ports in the front I/O (that are not available in the regular Wall Street Canyon kits), and VESA mounting support are all retained in the Newton WS.</p>

<h3>Plato WS</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/update.php?tpl=product/product.detail.tpl&amp;type=FANLESS%20CASES&amp;type_sub=Intel%20NUC&amp;model=A-NUC85-M1B">Plato WS</a> is a slim chassis (39mm in height) that builds upon user feedback for the previous Plato cases. The key update over the Plato TN is the integration of support for the front panel audio jack.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/plato-ws_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The Plato WS carries over all the other attractive aspects of the product family - VESA and rack mounting support, 2.5&quot; drive installation support, serial port in the rear I/O, and additional USB 2.0 ports in the front panel.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/plato-ws-int_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>In addition to the above three SKUs, Akasa also recently launched the <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/update.php?tpl=product/product.detail.tpl&amp;type=FANLESS%20CASES&amp;type_sub=Intel%20NUC&amp;model=A-NUC67-M1B">Pascal TN</a>, a passively-cooled IP65-rated case for the Tiger Canyon and Wall Street Canyon NUCs, making it suitable for outdoor installations.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18723/pascal-tn_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>Akasa&#39;s main competition comes from fanless system vendors like <a href="https://www.onlogic.com/computers/industrial/fanless/ml100-series/">OnLogic</a> and <a href="https://www.cirrus7.com/en/produkte/cirrus7-nimbini/">Cirrus7</a> who prefer to sell pre-built systems with higher margins. In the DIY space, we have offerings like the <a href="https://hdplex.com/hdplex-h1-v3-fanless-computer-case.html">HDPLEX H1 V3</a> and <a href="https://hdplex.com/hdplex-h1-todd-fanless-computer-case.html">HDPLEX H1 TODD</a> which unfortunately do not have wide distribution channels like Akasa&#39;s products - as a result of lower volumes, the pricing is also a bit on the higher end. For Wall Street Canyon, Tranquil is also offering a <a href="https://tranquil-it.shop/compact-rugged-intel-12th-gen-case-kit/">DIY case</a> in addition to their usual <a href="https://tranquil-it.shop/fanless-nucs/">pre-built offerings</a>. It remains to be seen whether the company remains committed to the DIY space.</p>

<p>Passively-cooled cases usually have a significant price premium that regular consumers usually don&#39;t want to pay. Vendors like Akasa are bringing about a change in this category by offering reasonably-priced, yet compelling products via e-tailers. Simultaneous focus on industrial deployments and OEM contracts as well as consumer retail has proved successful for Akasa, as evidenced by their continued commitment to thermal solutions for different NUC generations.</p>

<p><div>Gallery: <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221" target="_blank">CES 2023: Akasa Introduces Fanless Cases for Wall Street Canyon NUCs</a><div><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221#1" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8221/carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221#2" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8221/newton-ws-01_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221#3" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8221/newton-ws-02_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221#4" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8221/pascal-tn_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221#5" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8221/plato-ws-int_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8221#6" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8221/plato-ws_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a></div></div></p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://akasa.co.uk/update.php?tpl=list%2FCHASSIS+POWER.tpl&amp;type=FANLESS+CASES&amp;type_sub=Intel+NUC&amp;fval=12th+Gen">Akasa</a>, <a href="https://www.fanlesstech.com/2023/01/premium-akasa-case-solutions-for-intel.html">FanlessTech</a></p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18723/ces-2023-akasa-introduces-fanless-cases-for-wall-street-canyon-nucs</link>
 	<pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 06:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18723:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Trade Shows]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>CES 2023: IOGEAR Introduces USB-C Docking Solutions and Matrix KVM</title>
    <dc:creator>Ganesh T S</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18722/ces-2023-iogear-introduces-usbc-docking-solutions-and-matrix-kvm"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18722/carousel_crop_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>IOGEAR has been servicing the computer accessories market with docks and KVMs for more than a couple of decades now. In addition to the generic use-cases, the company creates products that target niche segments with feature sets that are not available in products from other vendors. At CES 2023, IOGEAR is taking the wraps off a number of USB-C docks slated to get introduced over the next couple of quarters.</p>

<h3>Docking Solutions</h3>

<p>The three new products in this category fall under two categories - the first two utilize Display Link chips along with traditional USB-C Alt Mode support, while the third one uses the Intel Goshen Ridge Thunderbolt controller for 8K support in addition to the usual array of ports found in regular Thunderbolt 4 / USB4 docks. The following table summarizes the essential aspects of the three new products.</p>

<table style="width: 100%;">
	<tbody>
		<tr class="tgrey">
			<td align="center" colspan="4" style="vertical-align: middle;">IOGEAR USB-C Docking Solutions @ CES 2023 (Dock Pro Series)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr align="center" class="tlblue">
			<td colspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">&nbsp;</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">Universal Dual View Docking Station</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">Duo USB-C Docking Station</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">USB4 8K Triple View</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Model Name</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">GUD3C4K2TAA</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">GUD3CDHTAA</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">GUD4C8K3</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Upstream Port</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">USB 3.2 Gen 2 Type-C</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x USB 3.2 Gen 2 Type-C (Dual Host Support)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">USB4 Type-C (40 Gbps)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Audio</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x 3.5mm Combo Audio Jack</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x Mic In<br />
			1x Speaker Out</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x 3.5mm Combo Audio Jack</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">USB-A</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x USB 3.2 Gen 1<br />
			1x USB 3.2 Gen 1 (12W charging)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x USB 2.0<br />
			2x USB 3.2 Gen 2</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x USB 3.2 Gen 2<br />
			1x USB 3.2 Gen 1</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">USB-C</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x USB 3.2 Gen 2</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x USB 3.2 Gen 2</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x USB 3.2 Gen 2<br />
			2x USB4 (40Gbps with DP Alt Mode up to 8Kp30) downstream</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Networking</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x GbE RJ-45</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x GbE RJ-45</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x 2.5 GbE RJ-45</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Card Reader</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">-</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">-</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">1x SDXC UHS-II<br />
			1x microSDXC UHS-II</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Display Outputs</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x HDMI 2.0a<br />
			2x Display Port 1.2a<br />
			(All via DisplayLink Chipset)<br />
			(Max. of 2x 4Kp60 Outputs)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x Display Port 1.2a (4Kp60) (via DisplayLink Chipset)<br />
			1x HDMI 1.4a (4Kp30) (via DP Alt Mode)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">2x HDMI 2.1 (up to 8Kp30)<br />
			2x Display Port 2.1 (up to 8Kp30)<br />
			(All via DP Alt Mode)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Host Power Delivery</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">USB PD 3.0 (up to 100W)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">Up to 100W per host (total 200W)</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">USB PD 3.0 (up to 96W)</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Power Supply</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">External 150W @ 20V/7.5A</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">External 230W</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">External 150W @ 20V/7.5A</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Dimensions</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">91mm x 70mm x 17mm</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">219mm x 88mm x 32mm</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">225mm x 85mm x 18mm</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">Launch Date</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">March 2023</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">June 2023</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">March 2023</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tlgrey" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle;">MSRP</td>
			<td colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">$250</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">$300</td>
			<td rowspan="1" style="vertical-align: middle; width: 27%;">$300</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>The Dock Pro Universal Dual View Docking Station is a premium DisplayLink-based dock capable of driving up to two 4Kp60 displays, with a choice of HDMI or DisplayPort for each.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18722/ces-2023-iogear-introduces-usbc-docking-solutions-and-matrix-kvm"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18722/dock-pro-dual-view_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The dock also includes host power delivery support, and the distribution of ports is presented above.</p>

<p>The Dock Pro Duo USB-C Docking Station is ostensibly a USB-C dock, but it incorporates features typically found in KVMs. It allows two systems to be simultaneously connected to the dock, and a push button in front to cycle between one of four display modes as show in the picture below.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18722/ces-2023-iogear-introduces-usbc-docking-solutions-and-matrix-kvm"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18722/dock-pro-duo_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The push button configures one of the two hosts to the DisplayLink chain (that is behind the two DisplayPort outputs). All the peripheral ports are seen by the host connected to that chain. At the same time, the HDMI port is kept active using the Alt Mode display output from the other host. Hot keys are available to cycle through the display modes to enable easy multi-tasking. This is an innovative combination of docking and KVM that I haven&#39;t seen from other vendors yet.</p>

<p>Finally, we have the flagship USB4 / Thunderbolt 4 dock - the Dock Pro USB4 8K Triple View. It incorporates all the bells and whistles one might want from a TB4 dock, including downstream USB4 ports and 8K support.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18722/ces-2023-iogear-introduces-usbc-docking-solutions-and-matrix-kvm"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18722/dock-pro-usb4-triple_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>Surprisingly, the pricing is quite reasonable at $300 - possibly kept that way by avoiding Thunderbolt certification. This product could appeal to a different audience compared to the Plugable TBT4-UDZ despite similar pricing, thanks to the availability of downstream ports. However, the product is slated to ship only towards the end of the quarter.</p>

<h3>KVM Solutions</h3>

<p>IOGEAR is also announcing the GCMS1922 2-port 4K Dual View DisplayPort Matrix KVMP with USB 3.0 Hub and Audio. Such KVMs with 4Kp60 support have typically been priced upwards of $500. This is no exception with a $530 MSRP. However, for this pricing, IOGEAR is incorporating a number of interesting features. The KVM can operate in either matrix or extension mode, with one computer driving both display outputs in the latter, and each host driving one display in the former. In the matrix mode, the KVM also supports crossover switching via movement of the mouse pointer (in addition to the regular physical button on the KVM and hotkeys). Audio mixing support (i.e, keeping the audio output of a &#39;disconnected&#39; host also active) is available too, allowing the monitoring of notifications from both computers without having to switch sources.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18722/ces-2023-iogear-introduces-usbc-docking-solutions-and-matrix-kvm"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18722/kvm-sol_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The KVM provides two USB 3.2 Gen 1 and two USB 2.0 Type-A ports for downstream peripherals in addition to separate audio jacks for the speaker and microphone. It must be noted that the display outputs are HDMI, while the inputs are DisplayPort. The KVM switch is slated to become available later this quarter.</p>

<p>In addition to these upcoming products, IOGEAR is also demonstrating the <a href="https://www.iogear.com/product/GCS1337/">KeyMander Nexus Gaming KVM</a> and the <a href="https://www.iogear.com/product/GKB610R">MECHLITE NANO</a> compact USB / wireless keyboard at the show. These products were introduced into the market last year.</p>

<p><div>Gallery: <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8219" target="_blank">CES 2023: IOGEAR Introduces USB-C Docking Solutions and Matrix KVM</a><div><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8219#1" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8219/carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8219#2" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8219/dock-pro-dual-view_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8219#3" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8219/dock-pro-duo_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8219#4" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8219/dock-pro-usb4-triple_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8219#5" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8219/kvm-sol_carousel_thumb.jpg" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a></div></div></p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18722/ces-2023-iogear-introduces-usbc-docking-solutions-and-matrix-kvm</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 11:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18722:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ Trade Shows]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>CES 2023: AMD Instinct MI300 Data Center APU Silicon In Hand - 146B Transistors, Shipping H2’23</title>
    <dc:creator>Ryan Smith</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/AMD_MI300_CES_Slide_575px.png" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>Alongside AMD&rsquo;s widely expected client product announcements this evening for desktop CPUs, mobile CPUs, and mobile GPUs, AMD&rsquo;s CEO Dr. Lisa Su also had a surprise up her sleeve for the large crowd gathered for her prime CES keynote: a sneak peak at MI300, AMD&rsquo;s next-generation data center APU that is currently under development. With silicon literally in hand, the quick teaser laid out the basic specifications of the part, along with reiterating AMD&rsquo;s intentions of taking leadership in the HPC market.</p>

<p>First unveiled by AMD during their 2022 Financial Analyst Day back in June of 2022, <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17445/amd-combining-cdna-3-and-zen-4-for-mi300-data-center-apu-in-2023">MI300 is AMD&rsquo;s first shot at building a true data center/HPC-class APU</a>, combining the best of AMD&rsquo;s CPU and GPU technologies. As was laid out at the time, MI300 would be a disaggregated design, using multiple chiplets built on TSMC&rsquo;s 5nm process, and using 3D die stacking to place them over a base die, all of which in turn will be paired with on-package HBM memory to maximize AMD&rsquo;s available memory bandwidth.</p>

<p>AMD for its part is no stranger to combining the abilities of its CPUs and GPUs &ndash; one only needs to look at their laptop CPUs/APUs &ndash; but to date they&rsquo;ve never done so on a large scale. AMD&rsquo;s current best-in-class HPC hardware is to combine the discrete AMD Instinct MI250X (a GPU-only product) with AMD&rsquo;s EPYC CPUs, which is exactly what&rsquo;s been done for the Frontier supercomputer and other HPC projects. MI300, in turn, is the next step in the process, bringing the two processor types together on to a single package, and not just wiring them up in an MCM fashion, but going the full chiplet route with TSV stacked dies to enable extremely high bandwidth connections between the various parts.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/MI300_Lisa_Crop.jpg" style="width: 678px; height: 515px;" /></a></p>

<p>The key point of tonight&rsquo;s reveal was to show off the MI300 silicon, which has reached initial production and is now in AMD&rsquo;s labs for bring-up. AMD had previously promised a 2023 launch for the MI300, and having the silicon back from the fabs and assembled is a strong sign that AMD is on track to make that delivery date.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/MI300_CES_575px.jpg" /></a><br />
<em>Up Close With MI300 (Image Courtesy <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-pictured-up-close-15-chiplets-146-billion-transistors">Tom&#39;s Hardware</a>)</em></p>

<p>Along with a chance to see the titanic chip in person (or at least, over a video stream), the brief teaser from Dr. Su also offered a few new tantalizing details about the hardware. At 146 billion transistors, MI300 is the biggest and most complex chip AMD has ever built &ndash; and easily so. Though we can only compare it to current chip designs, this is significantly more transistors than either Intel&rsquo;s 100B transistor Xeon Max GPU (Ponte Vecchio), or NVIDIA&rsquo;s 80B transistor GH100 GPU. Though in fairness to both, AMD is stuffing both a GPU and a CPU into this part.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/AMD_MI300_Specs_Teaser_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The CPU side of the MI300 has been confirmed to use 24 of AMD&rsquo;s Zen 4 CPU cores, finally giving us a basic idea of what to expect with regards to CPU throughput. Meanwhile the GPU side is (still) using an undisclosed number of CDNA 3 architecture CUs. All of this, in turn, is paired with 128GB of HBM3 memory.</p>

<p>According to AMD, MI300 is comprised of 9 5nm chiplets, sitting on top of 4 6nm chiplets. The 5nm chiplets are undoubtedly the compute logic chipets &ndash; i.e. the CPU and GPU chiplets &ndash; though a precise breakdown of what&rsquo;s what is not available. A reasonable guess at this point would be 3 CPU chiplets (8 Zen 4 cores each) paired with possibly 6 GPU chiplets; though there&#39;s still some cache chiplets unaccounted for. Meanwhile, taking AMD&rsquo;s &ldquo;on top of&rdquo; statement literally, the 6nm chiplets would then be the base dies all of this sits on top of. Based on AMD&rsquo;s renders, it looks like there&rsquo;s 8 HBM3 memory stacks in play, which implies around 5TB/second of memory bandwidth, if not more.</p>

<p>With regards to performance expectations, AMD isn&rsquo;t saying anything new at this time. Previous claims were for a &gt;5x improvement in AI performance-per-watt versus the MI250X, and an overall &gt;8x improvement in AI training performance, and this is still what AMD is claiming as of CES.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/MI300_Perf_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p>The key advantage of AMD&rsquo;s design, besides the operational simplicity of putting CPU cores and GPU cores on the same design, is that it will allow both processor types to share a high-speed, low-latency unified memory space. This would make it fast and easy to pass data between the CPU and GPU cores, letting each handle the aspects of computing that they do best. As well, it would significantly simplify HPC programming at a socket level by giving both processor types direct access to the same memory pool &ndash; not just a unified virtual memory space with copies to hide the physical differences, but a truly shared and physically unified memory space.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/2022-06-09%2013_46_36_575px.jpg" /></a><br />
<em>AMD FAD 2022 Slide</em></p>

<p>When it launches in the later half of 2023, AMD&rsquo;s MI300 is expected to be going up against a few competing products. The most notable of which is likely <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/16610/nvidia-unveils-grace-a-highperformance-arm-server-cpu-for-use-in-ai-systems">NVIDIA&rsquo;s Grace Hopper superchip</a>, which combines an NVIDIA Armv9 Grace CPU with a Hopper GPU. NVIDIA has not gone for quite the same level of integration as AMD is, which arguably makes MI300 a more ambitious project, though NVIDIA&rsquo;s decision to maintain a split memory pool is not without merit (e.g. capacity). Meanwhile, AMD&rsquo;[s schedule would have them coming in well ahead of arch rival Intel&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/17268/intel-goes-full-xpu-falcon-shores-to-combine-x86-and-xe-for-supercomputers">Falcon Shores XPU</a>, which isn&rsquo;t due until 2024.</p>

<p>Expect to hear a great deal more from AMD about Instinct MI300 in the coming months, as the company will be eager to show off their most ambitious processor to date.</p>

<p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223"><img alt="" src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18721/MI300_Release_Date_575px.jpg" /></a></p>

<p align="center"><div>Gallery: <a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8218" target="_blank">AMD CES 2023 Instinct MI300 Slides</a><div><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8218#1" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8218/AMD CES 2023 Keynote Deck_57_thumb.png" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8218#2" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8218/AMD CES 2023 Keynote Deck_58_thumb.png" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8218#3" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8218/AMD CES 2023 Keynote Deck_59_thumb.png" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/Gallery/Album/8218#4" target="_blank"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/galleries/8218/AMD CES 2023 Keynote Deck_60_thumb.png" width="85" height="85" border="0"/></a></div></div></p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18721/ces-2023-amd-instinct-mi300-data-center-apu-silicon-in-hand-146b-transistors-shipping-h223</link>
 	<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 07:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18721:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>AMD Unveils Ryzen 9 7950X3D, 7900X3D, and Ryzen 7 7800X3D, Up to 128 MB of L3 Cache And 5.7 GHz Boost</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>During Computex 22, AMD showcased its updated CPU roadmap going through 2024, which yielded some exciting propositions to the desktop processor market. One of those products highlighted was a new 3D V-Cache SKU based on Zen 4 cores, and with the success of its previous Ryzen 7 5800X3D with 96 MB of 3D stacked V-Cache, gamers have been chomping at the bit for more ever since. Using their primetime&nbsp;keynote slot during CES 2023, AMD has unveiled its next 3D V Cache-based processors to the market using its Zen 4 core architecture.</p>

<p>AMD hasn&#39;t unveiled just one new Zen 4-based X3D SKU; it&#39;s announcing three across the Ryzen 7000 series, the Ryzen 9 7950X3D, the Ryzen 9 7900X3D, and the Ryzen 7 7800X3D. Aside from 64 MB of additional L3 cache through AMD&#39;s 3D V-Cache stacking technology, which is a 3D chiplet stacking technology in conjunction with TSMC, all three Zen 4 X3D SKUs feature a 120 W TDP. They also have higher boost core frequencies than previous X3D chips, with the Ryzen 9 7950X3D boosting up to an impressive&nbsp;of&nbsp;5.7 GHz on the core.</p>
]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18709/amd-unveils-ryzen-9-7950x3d-7900x3d-and-ryzen-7-7800x3d-up-to-128-mb-of-l3-cache-and-5-7-ghz-boost</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 22:31:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18709:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
    
<item>
    <title>AMD Announces Ryzen 9 7900, Ryzen 7 7700, and Ryzen 5 7600 Processors: Zen 4 at 65 W</title>
    <dc:creator>Gavin Bonshor</dc:creator>    
    <description><![CDATA[ <p align="center"><a href="https://www.anandtech.com/show/18715/amd-announces-ryzen-9-7900-ryzen-7-7000-and-ryzen-5-7600-processors-zen-4-at-65-w"><img src="https://images.anandtech.com/doci/18715/Angled Socket Close Up 1_575px.jpg" alt="" /></a></p><p><p>During its keynote at CES 2023, Dr. Lisa Su, AMD&#39;s CEO, announced three new desktop processors based on its Zen 4 microarchitecture, the Ryzen 9 7900, Ryzen 7 7700, and Ryzen 5 7600. Each of these new processors includes a base TDP of 65 W with a reduction of all-core base frequency compared to the X-series SKUs.&nbsp;Designed to be a more affordable and cost-effective option for its latest AM5 platform, the new 65 W-based&nbsp;Ryzen 7000 SKUs come bundled with one of AMD&#39;s Wraith coolers, with prices starting at $229 for the Ryzen 5 7600.</p>

<p>With the ever-pressing desire for high-performance levels in the&nbsp;desktop space, but with even higher levels of performance per watt, AMD&#39;s unleashed three new derivatives of its existing Ryzen 7000 desktop CPUs. Still, with a base TDP of just 65 W,&nbsp;there is more to the story than bare TDP figures. AMD also uses Package Power Tracking (PPT) as a metric which typically sits higher; this is effectively the power levels given from the AM5 socket itself, coupled with Precision Boost Overdrive (PBO), which can yield increased levels of performance for at the&nbsp;cost of heat and power.</p>
</p>]]></description>
    <link>https://www.anandtech.com/show/18715/amd-announces-ryzen-9-7900-ryzen-7-7000-and-ryzen-5-7600-processors-zen-4-at-65-w</link>
 	<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 22:31:00 EDT</pubDate>
 	<guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.anandtech.com,18715:news</guid>
 	<category><![CDATA[ CPUs]]></category>                               
</item>  
    
</channel>
</rss>